<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Spiritual armour to defend the head from the superfluity of naughtiness being a loving and Christian tender, humbly offered to the pious and serious consideration of the ministers of the Gospel and to all others it may concern : wherein is proved that it is unlawful for women to cut their hair polled or shorn and men to wear the same to cover their heads : together with how men and women ought according to the written law of God and nature to wear their hair.</title>
            <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67327</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26304</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09418420</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09418420</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43039</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67327)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43039)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1319:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Spiritual armour to defend the head from the superfluity of naughtiness being a loving and Christian tender, humbly offered to the pious and serious consideration of the ministers of the Gospel and to all others it may concern : wherein is proved that it is unlawful for women to cut their hair polled or shorn and men to wear the same to cover their heads : together with how men and women ought according to the written law of God and nature to wear their hair.</title>
                  <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author and sold by William Marshall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: A loving and Christian tender humbly offered to the pious and serious cnsideration of the ministers of the Gospel and to all others it may concern.</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Tho. Wall.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hair --  Religious aspects.</term>
               <term>Sex role --  Biblical teaching.</term>
               <term>Women --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43039:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43039:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Spiritual Armour</hi> To Defend the HEAD FROM THE SUPERFLUITY of NAUGHTINNESS. Being a Loving and Chriſtian TENDER, Humbly offered to the Pious and Serious Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and to all others it may Concern.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN IS PROVED, That it is Unlawful for Women to cut their Hair polled or ſhorn; and Men to wear the ſame to cover their Heads: Together how Men and Women ought according to the Written Law of GOD and Nature to wear their Hair.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Stand ye in the Way, and ſee and ask for the old Path, where is the good Way,</hi> Jer. 6. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Woman ſhall not wear that which pertaineth unto a Man, neither ſhall a Man put on a Womans Garment; for all that do ſo, are abomination to the Lord,</hi> Deut. 22. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither ſhall they ſhave their Heads, nor ſuffer their Locks to grow long; they ſhall only poll their heads,</hi> Ezek. 44. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doth not even Nature it ſelf teach you, If a Man have long Hair, it is a ſhame to him?</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author, and Sold by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Marſhal,</hi> at the Sign of the Bible in <hi>Newgate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43039:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43039:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THE drift and intent of theſe Lines, is not to ſhew the many manners and ways the</hi> Pagans, <hi>or most part of the World, have or do wear their hair; but the main end is, to ſhew in what order God created Man in reſpect of his hair; and that the Lord in all Ages hath by his Servants called upon his redeemed ones, to keep his Order in Nature; yea, in reſpect of wearing their hair, as well as in other things, that ſo his Order in Nature be not broken in any thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as it is oft-times the pleaſure of God, to imploy on the Lords Meſſage to his People, the weak and deſpiſed ones, according to the Prayer of the Lord Jeſus to his Father,</hi> I thank thee, O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 25, 26.</note> becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the Wiſe and Prudent, and haſt revealed them unto Babes; even ſo, Father, for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight: <hi>So that they oft-times ſeeing their own inſufficiency for ſo great a Work, have pleaded with the Lord to be excuſed; but becauſe the Lord will ſend by whom he will ſend, he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them not to be afraid of the faces of the Perſons, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were great Perſons, and powerful in the World, but to reſt upon Gods Promiſe,</hi> For I am with thee to deliver thee; therefore gird up thy loins, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 1. 6, 7, 8, 17.</note> ariſe and ſpeak unto them all that I command thee,
<pb facs="tcp:43039:3"/> leſt I confound thee before them, or break thee in pieces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And although all extraordinary Meſſengers, as Prophets and Apoſtles, are ceaſed; yet God hath his ordinary Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whom he ſendeth with his Meſſage to his People,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai. 8. 20. 1 Joh.</hi> 4. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>according to his written Word, by which all Spirits or Doctrines muſt be tried, in all that Men write or ſpeak to inform the Lords People as the mind of God: And as of old God had ordained Prieſts and</hi> Levites <hi>to teach the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut. 33. 8, 11. Mal.</hi> 2. 7.</note> 
               <hi>People from the written Word of the Lord,</hi> Jacob <hi>Gods Judgment, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>his Law, whom the Prophets repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for neglect of this duty; ſo he hath ordained Paſtors and Teachers, now to teach to be instant in ſeaſon and out of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph. 4. Rom. 12. 1 Tim.</hi> 4. 1, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſeaſon, to reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all long-ſuffering and Doctrine: But when the Priests as well as the</hi> Levites <hi>neglected their Duty, to have compaſſion on the Man that fell among Thieves, wounded, stripped of his Raiment, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. 31, 32, 33.</note> 
               <hi>left half dead (in Sins and Treſpaſſes) then by the example of the</hi> Samaritan, <hi>other Chriſtians Duty it is to have compaſſion on every poor Soul fallen into ſin: Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Paſtors and Teachers in this Day, whoſe Duty in this Treatiſe ſhall be ſhewed, ought to have compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on ſuch of their Brethren as are fallen into ſin; as this ſinful ſhame for Men to wear the long Hair of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in Perriwigs, but do not; then it is the Duty of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whom the Lord Jeſus biddeth go and do as the</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan <hi>did, though he be no Pastor, Priest, nor</hi> Levite <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk. 10. 37. Levit.</hi> 19. 17.</note> 
               <hi>in Office; and thoſe that ſo do, are the only Neighbours to thoſe fallen into ſin, wounded in Conſcience, that do pour the Oyl, or Name, or Goſpel of Christ; which being</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>applied to the wounded in ſin, is as Ointment poured forth; whereby the hanging-down hands is lifted up, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>feeble knees is strengthned.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43039:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>This being the very end of this Work, in a day of ſo great neceſſity, when ſin, not only this, the ſhame to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is ſuffered, but many other Evils in the Churches in this day, for which Judgment ere long will begin at</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 17.</note> 
               <hi>the Houſe of God, as it did on the Primitive Churches, as Mr.</hi> Fuller <hi>in his Hiſtory of the</hi> Holy Wars <hi>hath ſhewed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Fullers <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the holy Wars, p. 6. c.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>in theſe words:</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>The Sins of the Eaſtern Countries, chiefly their damnable Hereſies, haſtned Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on them; and in the Western parts, Hereſies as an Angle caught ſingle perſons; when in</hi> Aſia, <hi>like a Draw-Net, it took whole Provinces: the ſtaid Wits of</hi> Europe <hi>were not ſo eaſily removed out of the old road and track of Religion, whilſt the active and nimble Heads of the East, were more deſirous of Novelties, more deſirous and cunning to invent diſtinctions to cozen themſelves, more fluent in Language to expreſs their Conceits; as always Errour groweth faſteſt in hotteſt Brains: Hence it was the</hi> Melkites, Maronites, Neſtorians, Euticheans, Jacobites, <hi>overſpread thoſe parts; then it was just with God to ſuffer them that would not be convinced by Chriſtian Counſel, to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by the</hi> Pagans <hi>Sword. And again, It may ſeem admirable, that that ſenceleſs Religion ſhould gain ſo much ground on Christianiſm, eſpecially having neither real ſubstance in Doctrine, nor winning Behaviour in Ceremony to alure Profeſſors; being but the ſcum of</hi> Judaiſm <hi>and</hi> Paganiſm <hi>ſod together, and here and there ſtrowed over with a ſpice of Christianity.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If this be not a word in ſeaſon, to conſider how like this</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. 1, 17.</note> 
               <hi>is to the day we live in, when the last Vial of Gods wrath is poured into an earthen Air, as Air is likened to Wind or Doctrine, how is it that Men ſee not how all Doctrine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>is corrupted, not only of Faith, but the Doctrine of the Moral Law? fitting all for Judgment, the great ſign of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 8.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:43039:4"/> 
               <hi>the latter Day approaching near, as the days of</hi> Noe, <hi>then</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. 24. 37. 1 Pet. 3. 20. Rev. 16. 15. Mat.</hi> 24. 43.</note> 
               <hi>ſcarce Faith found in eight Souls. Now the Kingdom of Heaven is likened to ten Virgins, half naught; and will not the Church be awakened, Chriſt will come as a Thief,</hi> Bleſſed is he that watcheth and keepeth his Garment; <hi>and not be found in as miſerable condition, as the Church of</hi> Laodicea, <hi>when ſhe boaſted ſhe was rich</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>and wanted nothing, then was ſhe wretched, miſerable, poor, blind, and naked. The Lord help all therefore to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5.</note> 
               <hi>examine the ſtate they are in, and to make their calling and election ſure, that ſo they may be ready when Chriſt cometh, to enter in with Christ into the Joy of their Lord;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10.</note> 
               <hi>which is and ſhall be the Prayer of him who is thine in all Christian Duty,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Wall.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43039:4"/>
            <head>A Loving and Chriſtian Tender, humbly offered to the Pious and Serious Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Ministers of the Goſpel, and to all others it may concern.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as we are taught <note n="a" place="margin">Eccl. 3. 1, 7.</note> 
               <hi>to every thing there is a ſeaſon, and a time to every purpoſe under the Heaven;</hi> ſo that I humbly conceive, as <hi>there is a time to keep ſilence,</hi> and <hi>there is a time to ſpeak:</hi> It is now in theſe laſt days of Apoſtacy, when the Miniſters of that glorious Name, or Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who are taught by the Apoſtle, to be Examples to the Believers, <note n="b" place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 12.</note> in Word, in Converſation, in Charity or Love, in Spirit, in Faith, in Purity; ſo that among other Proofs of their Miniſtry, that the Miniſtry be not blam'd, they may approve themſelves to be the Miniſters of Chriſt by pureneſs, do <note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 3, 6.</note> on the contrary, oppoſite to Purity or Pureneſs, give an evil Example to the Believers, in walking in the ſhame to their Nature, either in ſuffering their Locks to grow long, and otherſome in wearing the Locks of Women in Perriwigs, contrary to the expreſs <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 20.</note> Word of God and light <note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 14.</note> of Nature, whereby they have chang'd the natural uſe, into that which is againſt Nature; which is a great diſhonour to God our Creator, and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reproach and diſgrace to the Chriſtian Religion, as ſhall by the help of God be made to appear; and that this evil being winkt at by the Miniſters, is the inlet to many other evils in the Churches of God.</p>
            <p>And although I do acknowledge my ſelf the unfitteſt of any to undertake a work of this nature, yet ſeeing the Miniſters
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43039:5"/> whoſe work it is, to ſet the <note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 58. 1.</note> Trump of Gods Word to their mouths, as the Prieſts lips of old was to preſerve Knowledge; yet when the Prieſts omitted their Duty, as it is written <note n="g" place="margin">Jer. 2. 8. Mal. 2. 7.</note> 
               <hi>The Prieſt ſaid not, Where is the Lord? they that handled the Law knew me not; the Paſtors tranſgreſſed againſt me:</hi> So that God called <hi>Amos</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Amos 7. 14, 16.</note> a Herdſman, a gatherer of Sycamore Fruit, to drop the Word of the Lord againſt the Houſe of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> even ſo when the Prieſt and Teacher of the Law in the days of Chriſt, neglected to teach the weighty matters of the Law, <note n="i" place="margin">Matth. 23. 23.</note> Mercy, Judgment, and Faith; the Lord called poor <note n="k" place="margin">Matth. 4. 19.</note> Fiſhermen to preach the Kingdom of God; therefore let none be offended, becauſe God hath choſen the <note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 27, 28, 29.</note> fooliſh and baſe things of the World, the things that are deſpiſed, even Babes in Chriſt, that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence, whenas the Learned in this day are altogether ſilent, ſome peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture through ſlaviſh fear, do not reprove this ſin, the ſhame to Nature, in Mens wearing of long Hair, leſt they ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Rich among them; others being themſelves guilty of this ſin, in wearing long Hair, the ſhame to Nature, do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thoſe that do wear long Hair; ſo that the work of God in this thing is wholly neglected, as in ſome other things not here to mention; therefore for the honour of God, and the love I bear to all Gods elected Children that are fallen <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 24. 24.</note> into this ſin, have I made bold to ſhew my Opinion, as one that hath obtained mercy; knowing aſſuredly, that all that ſhall read theſe lines, that have like ſpirit with <hi>David,</hi> will not be offended, but rather with like gracious heart will ſay with him, <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 141. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Let the Righteous ſmite me, and it ſhall be a kindneſs; and let him reprove me, and it ſhall be an excellent Oyl that ſhall not break my head;</hi> becauſe to ſuch who have the ſeed of Gods <note n="o" place="margin">Luk. 8. 15. 1 Joh. 3. 9. Job. 19. 28.</note> Word in their hearts, <note n="p" place="margin">Prov. 27. 5, 6, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Open rebuke is better to them than ſecret love, and faithful are the wounds of a friend; whenas the kiſſes of an enemy are deceitful:</hi> Therefore ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> him that juſtifieth the wicked, the people ſhall curſe; but to them that rebuketh, ſhall be pleaſantneſs; and upon him ſhall come <note n="q" place="margin">Prov. 24. 24, 29.</note> the bleſſing: So then to the Law, and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 20.</note> there is no light in them.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43039:5"/>
            <p>Now becauſe the matter here to be treated of, is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the breach of Gods order in Nature, for the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thereof, it is good we take ſome obſervation concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the holy Order God created Man and Woman in, as they were purely natural, foraſmuch as that was not firſt which is ſpiritual, but that which <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 46.</note> is natural.</p>
            <p>Therefore we read God who created all things for his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <note n="s" place="margin">Rev. 4. 11.</note> made every thing perfectly good, <note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 1. 31.</note> ſet in moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and happy order; Man, the Lord created after his own Image; in the Image of God created he him, Male and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male created he <note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 1 27.</note> them: ſo that Man among other Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Nature, bore Gods Image in <note n="w" place="margin">verſ. 26.</note> Soveraignty, being Lord of the Earth <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 8. 6, 7, 8.</note> and Sea; chief Ruler under God over all the plenty therein; ſo that Man of all earthly Creatures, was made in ſubjection to God only; and hereupon Man is called the Glory <note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 7.</note> of God.</p>
            <p>The Woman God made for Man of his own kind, given to Man by God in a Marriage-ſtate <note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 22. 22, 23.</note> for comfort and procre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of his own kind: She alſo was made in, ſubjection to Man, her earthly Lord and Husband; and hereupon is Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man called the <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 7.</note> Glory of a Man.</p>
            <p>This being that holy Order God created Man and Woman in; the Man the Womans <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 2.</note> head, the Woman in ſubjection to Man; the Man the Glory <note n="c" place="margin">verſ. 7.</note> of God; the Woman the Glory of the Man; it was, therefore the pleaſure of God to give unto Woman a ſign in nature differing from Man, to teach her ſubjection to Man whoſe Glory ſhe is, namely long hair; and that Man was created with ſhort hair; is alſo clear; for in the Apoſtles reproving Men in the Church of God at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> for wearing of long hair, his Reaſons by way of reproof is grounded on Gods order in Nature; as it is written, <hi>Doth not even Nature it ſelf teach you, if a man have long hair it is a ſhame to him:</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 14.</note> So then <hi>Adam</hi> was created ſo perfect in Nature, that there was not anything about him, inwardly or outwardly, whereof he might be aſham'd: And then to Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man he ſaith, in reproving her for wearing her Hair uncove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſaying, <hi>If a woman have long hair, it is a glory</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">verſ. 15.</note> 
               <hi>to her;</hi> ſhewing the reaſon from Gods order in Nature, why Womans
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43039:6"/> long hair is a glory to her, <hi>For her hair is given her for a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring;</hi> to wit, of her Eyes, becauſe it is written <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. 16.</note> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Womans ſign of her ſubjection to Man her Husband, a Husband is to his Wife a covering of the Eyes; ſo then we ſee why Womans hair was called long, and why the Apoſtle ſaith, if a Woman have long hair it is a glory to her; for her hair is given her for a covering, namely to cover her Eyes, to teach her ſhe is under the power of Man her Husband, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of her Eyes; by which it is clear, Mans hair in Creation was ſo ſhort, that it could not be made to ſerve for a covering to cover his Eyes: Now if Mans hair had been ſo long, it would have bore the name, Long-hair, and ſo a ſhame to his manly Nature to wear, being the like badge and ſign of Womans ſubjection to Man her Husband, foraſmuch as Womans hair is called long, becauſe for length it was given her for a covering to cover her Eyes, for the reaſon aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Again, the Sin Fall did no way leſſen the power the Man had over his Wife before the Fall, neither Womans ſubjection to Man her Husband; and this the Apoſtle would have the Church of God to know, ſaying, <note n="g" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 2.</note> 
               <hi>The head of every man is Chriſt; the head of the woman is the man:</hi> So that as before the Fall, Womans long hair was a glory to her, ſo it is ſtill, as it is written, <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>If a woman have long hair, it is a glory to her, for her hair is given her for a covering:</hi> So then all the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Fall made in reſpect to Gods Order in Nature; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before the Fall, Womans long hair was the only viſible ſign of her ſubjection to Man her Husband; now by reaſon of ſin, and becauſe ſhe was the Inſtrument to draw her Lord into ſin with her; her glory therefore became her ſhame; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her hair muſt be decently bound up and cover'd: yet the ſame thing Womans long hair taught her before the Fall, the ſame her long hair teacheth her ſince: If it were not ſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle would not have taught, <hi>If a woman have long hair, it is a glory to her;</hi> although ſhe muſt cover it with a vail, as the Apoſtle hath taught, ſaying, <hi>Judge in your ſelves, is it come by for a woman to pray unto God</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 13.</note> 
               <hi>uncovered?</hi> And again, <hi>If the woman be not covered, let her alſo be</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>ſhorn:</hi> By this word, if the Woman cover not her head, and ſo her hair; let her
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43039:6"/> alſo be ſhorn, is clearly taught, how Man was created in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his hair; for the word alſo <hi>Be ſhorn,</hi> implieth, Mans hair was ſo, becauſe the whole grounds of the Apoſtle in all his reproofs, is taken from Gods Order in Creation; ſo by this word <hi>Shorn,</hi> is ſhew'd how Man is to wear his hair: ſo they that will not ſee this, muſt wink with <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 13.</note> the eye, ſeeing the Apoſtle ſetteth Mans ſhort hair, by the word <hi>Shorn,</hi> in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Womans long hair; which if ſhe cover it not, then ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Let her alſo be ſhorn,</hi> as Mans hair is to be, But again ſaith he, <hi>If it be a ſhame for a woman to be</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ſhorn,</hi> as Man was created in reſpect of the manner of his hair, or as Man is ever ſince the Creation to wear his hair, except as Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative or Ceremonial, (as in the <hi>Nazarites</hi> onely) <hi>let her be cover'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, as aforeſaid, as Womans long hair before the Fall was a glory to her, ſo it is ſtill, although ſhe muſt cover it: even ſo as Nature it ſelf taught Man before the Fall, that if he had long hair, it teacheth him ſo ſtill, that 'tis a ſhame to him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe the Men in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> did not only wear a womaniſh length of hair, but they alſo wore on their heads Womens Vails; ſo that in reproving them both, the Apoſtle teacheth, ſaying, <hi>Every man praying, or propheſying with his head</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 11. 4.</note> 
               <hi>covered, diſhonoureth his head;</hi> that is, he diſhonoureth his Head Chriſt: This is not meant in wearing a Cap, or the like; for Gods Miniſters of old wore ſuch in the Service <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod. 28. 40. Ezek.</hi> 44. 18.</note> of God, yet broke not Gods Order in Nature: So that Covering Man is forbidden to wear on his head in the Service of God, is that which is Womans natural Coverings; to wit, either a womaniſh length of hair, or Womans natural hair, or Womans vail, ſhe covereth her head, and ſo her hair withal; and this the Apoſtle proveth by an undeniable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from Gods Order in Creation, as it is written, <note n="p" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 7.</note> 
               <hi>For a man indeed ought not to cover his head, for aſmuch as he is the image and glory of God; but the woman is the glory of the man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we have heard Man beareth Gods <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26.</note> Image in Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, being head of the Woman; for the Woman was created under obedience <note n="q" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 34.</note> to Mani ſo is ſhe the glory of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43039:7"/> Man, and her long hair as given her for a ſign thereof. Now if Man do wear on his head long hair, Womans glory, he thereby ſaith by that action, He is no longer the Womans head; ſo doth he deſpiſe Gods Order in Creation, and ſaith he beareth not the Image <note n="r" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 5.</note> of God in Soveraignty over his Wife; but maketh himſelf equal with his Wife in power, and thereby diſhonoureth Chriſt his head and Creator, that made Man head of the Woman, and the glory of God: and this is ſuch a ſin, that 'tis not to be ſuffer'd in any true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 16.</note> of GOD; becauſe Man who is made the glory of God, in wearing Womens ſign in Nature that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth her ſhe is the glory of Man, breaketh Gods holy Order in Nature, which the Apoſtle confirmeth by Reaſon, from the State or Order of the Man or Womans Creation: His firſt Reaſon is, <hi>For the man is not of the woman, but the woman of the</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin"> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 8, 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>man.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Neither was the man created for the woman, but the woman for the man:</hi> For this cauſe ought the Woman to have power on her head; that is, a covering, in ſign that ſhe is under the power of her Husband; and from another reaſon, becauſe of the Angels, who being an innumerable company <note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 22.</note> round about the Throne of Chriſt in his Church, are Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb. 1. 14. 1 Tim.</hi> 5. 21.</note> with the Lord, of all the charges laid on the Saints to keep, when they joyn themſelves to the Lord, as well his Order in Nature, as in things Spiritual; ſo are we a ſpectacle to thoſe <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa. 104. 4. Mark 4. 6. Pſal. 91. 11. 1 Cor.</hi> 11. 10.</note> glorious Flames, who have a charge to keep us in all our ways: ſo are they miniſtring Spirits, ſent forth to miniſter for them who ſhall be Heirs of Salvation: For this cauſe the Apoſtle ſeemeth to require of Women modeſt and ſubmiſſive Attire, not only becauſe of Men, but becauſe of the Angels.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if there had been no certain Rule to judge or meaſure, or try when Mens hair is long by the golden Reed <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. 15.</note> of Gods Word, it had been a vain thing for the Apoſtles to reprove the Men in the Church of God, for wearing long hair, in theſe words: <note n="w" place="margin"> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Doth not even nature it ſelf teach you, if a man have long hair, it is a ſhame to him?</hi> Now the Rule in Nature to judge by is, from the Order of God in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, why Womens hair is called long, and ſo a glory to her;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43039:7"/> but the reaſon in Nature why Womens hair is called long, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 15.</note> it was given her for a covering, namely to cover her eyes; becauſe by this ſign in Nature, Woman is taught ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to Man her Husband, the covering of her <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. 16.</note> Eyes; ſo then it is clear from the Order of God in Nature, that that Man which weareth his hair ſo long, that it can by drawing it forward be made to ſerve to perform the end in the ſign that God gave Woman long hair for, to wit, for a covering to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Eyes, is the long hair even Nature it ſelf teacheth Man is a ſhame to his Nature to wear: So then as Sin is the cauſe of ſhame, <note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 3. 7. 10. Exod. 32. 25.</note> and Sin pollutes and makes the perſons unclean, and no unclean <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epl. 5. 5. Rev.</hi> 21. 27.</note> perſon ſhall enter into the City of God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are taught, that the Lord hath given a Command, to meaſure not only the Temple of God, and the Altar, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 1.</note> Worſhippers therein: Now the Worſhippers are the Members; therefore they muſt be hew'd off from their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt natural <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 24.</note> ſtock, by the Axe <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 10.</note> of Gods word, and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the waſhing of <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 16.</note> Water by the Word, from all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note n="e" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1, 2.</note> of the Fleſh and Spirit, before they can be laid as living <note n="f" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5.</note> Stones, joyn'd together in the Lords ſpiritual Building: For if in the figurative Building, no common or vile thing was uſed therein, but every Stone had its glory, and every Stone had its burden, all hew'd and ſquared fit; ſo then now we are to believe, as long hair is a ſhame, and not a glory to Man, that this ſhameful thing was cut off, by the word ſhorn or pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, from every Man before he was accepted as fit Stones to be ſet in the Lords ſpiritual Building in his Goſpel Churches. Now when the Stones were fitly ſquared and laid, then all things were to watch <note n="g" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 23.</note> one over another. But when the watch &amp; care that Members ſhould have, one over another was neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Churches of God, in not diſcharging their duty: If any one be overtaken <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1.</note> in a fault, he was to be reſtored in the Spirit of Meekneſs. This being not done in the Church at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> when Men ſuffer'd their locks to grow long, no Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd his Brother; ſo it is in this day, which was the reaſon the Apoſtle writ to them, and reprov'd them and all the Churches now in them, and all Members that ſuffer like diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the Churches of God.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43039:8"/>
            <p>Now then if long hair in Men were not ſuch a ſpot of ſin in the Church of God, as ſome would ſuppoſe, what need the Apoſtle to have us'd means to cleanſe them in the Church of God at <hi>Corinth</hi> from it, by the waſhing of Water by the word, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 26.</note> 
               <hi>I reproved them,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Doth not even Nature it ſelf teach you, That if a Man have long hair, it is a ſhame to him:</hi> For as the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 9.</note> Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Wherewith ſhall a young Man cleanſe his Way? by taking heed thereunto, according to thy Word.</hi> But who is it in this day, taketh heed to his way, in wearing long hair, the ſhame to Nature? Or what Congregation taketh any heed hereunto, according to Gods Word, to ſee this diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Nature reformed among them? If the breach of Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der had not been a Sin in Men's wearing long hair, the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> had not been reproved. But foraſmuch as it was then, ſo 'tis now become a Church Sin; Therefore we are taught, if the Congregation commit a Sin, they muſt bring their <hi>Offering,</hi> as 'tis written, <hi>If the whole Congregation of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 4. 19.</note> Iſrael <hi>ſin through Ignorance, and the thing be hid from the Eyes of the Aſſembly, and they have done ſomewhat againſt any of the Commandments of the Lord, concerning things which ſhould not be done, and are guilty; when the Sin which they have ſinn'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it is known, then the Congregation muſt bring their Sin-Offering:</hi> Even ſo when the Lord by his Servant <hi>John</hi> repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2, 3.</note> the five Churches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> each of them for a Church-ſin, in ſuffering ſinful Practices among them; The Lord called them to repent, to confeſs and forſake their Sins by an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Repentance,</hi> elſe the Lord would fight againſt them, and <hi>remove their Candleſtick,</hi> and <hi>kill her Children with Death.</hi> Now then 'tis clear, This Sin of Mens wearing long hair, and Women cutting their hair, ſhorn or polled, is become a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 23.</note> Church-ſin, who then that <hi>feareth the Lord among them,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the Fear of the Lord is to hate and depart from Evil,</hi> can <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov. 8. 13. Prov. 13. 13, 14. Joſh.</hi> 7.</note> have Communion with that Church, that liveth but in the breach of ſome <hi>One Commandment</hi> of the Lord, unleſs they <hi>repent and forſake the Evil?</hi> For was not the whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation puniſh'd for <hi>Achans</hi> Sin, when the Congregation was ignorant thereof? But what Wrath may be expected on that Congregation that knowingly—liveth in the breach, not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43039:8"/> of one, but of three Commands of God that forbiddeth Man in this particular thing, that Men and Women ſhould not break his holy Order in Nature: The firſt is the Moral Law, the Law written in every Man and Womans heart, teaching <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 15.</note> them that they ought, and may not do any act or thing that is againſt Nature; but according to the light in Nature, and Doctrine of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> for a Man to have, that is, to wear long hair, it is a ſhame to him, ſo a breach of the Moral Law. Secondly, That Law is broken that ſaith a Man ſhall not put on a Womans Garment; that is, any covering, that is Womens natural covering: But long hair is Womens na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 5.</note> covering; therefore that Man that weareth Womans hair on his head, weareth Womens natural covering, and ſo liveth in the breach of this Law alſo. Thirdly, a third Law is, Man ſhall not ſuffer his locks to grow long; and what is meant by long hair forbidden Man to wear, hath afore been <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 20.</note> ſhewed, when it can be made to ſerve to perform the end, to wit, the end in the ſign God gave in Nature, Women long hair, namely, for a covering to cover her Eye, to teach her ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Man, whoſe glory ſhe is; ſo is he to her by that ſign a covering to her Eyes.</p>
            <p>Now then where can it be ſhewed, that God when he called his People out from the World, that he accepted them into the Covenant of Grace with himſelf, until they were by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance cleanſed from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit; that <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1.</note> is, error in Faith, falſe Worſhip, and diſorder in Nature; which is the next thing in order to be confidered.</p>
            <p>We read, when God called his People out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> they were to be cleanſed from the Idols of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and all the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Nature they had learned among them, before they were joyn'd to the Lord; becauſe the Lord is holy, and therefore they were required to be holy in all manner of Converſation. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 15.</note> Now being cleanſed from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, hear what the Lord ſaid concerning them (after they were degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 5.</note> to put them in mind what a holy People they were, when they entered into the Covenant of Grace with the Lord; as 'tis written, <hi>I remember thee, the kindneſs of thy youth, the love of thine Eſpouſal. When thou wenteſt after me in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 2, 1, 2.</note> Iſreal <hi>was holineſs to the Lord;</hi> a holy Nation, a pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Treaſure to the Lord. The manner of this Marriage-Covenant
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43039:9"/> was, <hi>Thou hast avouched this day the Lord to be thy God, and to walk in his ways, and to keep his Statutes, and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 26. 16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; Judgments, &amp; to hearkento his voice. And the Lord hath avouched thee this day, to be his peculiar people; as he hath promiſed thee, and that thou ſhouldſt keep all his Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then were they charg'd to be Loyal to their Head and Husband, in keeping his Commandments; as it is written, <hi>After the doings of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>wherein ye dwelt, ſhall ye</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 18. 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>not do; after the doings of the Land of</hi> Canaan, <hi>whether I bring you, ſhall ye not do; neither ſhall ye walk in their ordinance: Ye ſhall do my Judgments, and keep my Ordinances to walk therein: I am the Lord.</hi> Thus were they to keep themſelves clear from all the Idolatry of thoſe People; and becaaſe they were not to do after the manner of the People, in the breach of Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 5.</note> in Nature, as they were now cleanſed, ſo they ſhould walk as the Lord commanded them, ſaying, <hi>A woman ſhall not wear that which pertaineth to man; neither ſhall a man put on womans garment; for all that do ſo, are an abomination to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now will not the People of God in this day conſider this, That whatſoever Man or Woman that liveth in the breach of Gods Order in Nature, even in the things they wear, they are abomination to the Lord. What then is Woman forbidden to wear, to wit, that pertaineth to Man, but that which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally pertaineth to Man? And what more naturally pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to Man, but ſhort hair? becauſe even Nature it ſelf teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>If a man have long hair, it is a ſhame to him,</hi> &amp;c. and that 'tis cloſely taught by the Apoſtle, that 'tis a ſhame for a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to be ſhorn or ſhaven; as 'tis written, <hi>If it be a ſhame for a woman to be ſhorn or ſhaven, let her be cover'd again:</hi> Likewiſe <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 6.</note> a Man ſhall not put on a Womans garment; that is, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is Womans natural covering: but long hair is giver to Woman for her natural covering; therefore long hair is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Womans glory, but Mans ſhame. By all which 'tis clear, That that Woman that cutteth her hair, ſhorn or polled, like <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 15.</note> as Man is to wear his hair, as before ſhew'd; and that Man that does ſuffer his locks to grow long, according to what afore hath been prov'd in long hair, and that even Nature it ſelf teacheth what is long hair; or that Man that weareth on his head the long hair of Woman, cut from Womens head, do live in no leſs ſin than that they have againſt Gods Order in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43039:9"/> Nature, chang'd the Natural uſe into that which is againſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. 22.</note> Nature; and in ſo doing in this particular thing, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing that is done againſt Nature, and daily live in, they are, as ſaith the Scripture, abomination to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now ſhall any Chriſtian Man and Woman, that is put in mind, what God in his written word, hath in theſe things warn'd them of not to err, leſt they incur to themſelves Gods ſore diſpleaſure? Or ſhall Chriſtians account it a light thing, to live in the known breach of Gods Law: yea, not only this <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 5.</note> Law, but the Moral Law written in every Mans heart; which teacheth Man that he ſhall not do any act or thing that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Nature, as aforeſaid: But 'tis againſt Nature for any Chriſtian Man to wear long hair, in ſuffering his own locks to grow long, as aforeſaid; how much more is it againſt Nature, for a Man to wear on his head the long locks of Women, Womans natural covering, Womans glory, Womans badge and ſign of Womans ſubjection to Man her Husband; a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice never ſuffered in any true Church of God, becauſe 'tis a ſin of a high nature; for, as aforeſaid, ſhort hair pertaineth to Man, and long hair pertaineth to Woman. Now for a Woman to cut her hair ſhort or ſhorn; ſhort by her ears, and on her forehead; and for a Man to cover his head with that long hair, Womans covering, is clearly, as aforeſaid, to change the natural uſe, into that which is againſt Nature. How can theſe be accounted the true Church of God, that know not Gods Order in Nature? If they do know it, then 'tis nigh to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 19. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2 Pet. 2. 10 Numb. 15. 30. Levit. 19. 2 Tim.</hi> 21.</note> the ſin of preſumption, to live knowingly in the breach of Gods Order in Nature: How can ſuch have any grounds to believe they can accepted of the Lord in his ſervice, ſeeing the Lord will be ſanctified in all that draw near unto him, in keeping his holy Order in Nature, as his Order in his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and that the perſon muſt firſt be accepted of God, before his Offering or Service can be, as Veſſels ſanctified, prepared fit for the Maſter the Lord Jeſus Chriſts uſe, in his ſervice.</p>
            <p>To add hereunto that which Mr. <hi>Henry Ainſworth</hi> hath noted out of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Writers, on theſe Words: <hi>A Woman ſhall not wear that which pertaineth to man;</hi> among other things they ſay, <hi>A Woman may not put on a Mans Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, or to poll her head like a Man; and a Man that putteth on a Womens Attire, and a Woman that putteth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Mans, is</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:43039:10"/> 
               <hi>to be beaten by the Magiſtrate.</hi> To which he alſo gveth his underſtanding of this Precept, ſaying it concerneth natural honeſty and ſeemlineſs, which hath perpetual Equity; his proof is 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 4, 5, 6, 14, &amp;c. It was given to prevent many evils that may ariſe: ſo that the Attire of the Body, ſignifieth the Ornament of the Mind, <hi>Pſal. 132. 9, 16. Rev.</hi> 3. 18. So Men ſhould not change their Natures to become effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and <hi>Babylonians,</hi> threatned to be like Women, <hi>Iſai. 19. 16. Jer.</hi> 50. 32. &amp; 5. 30.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Again, when the Lord after ſeventy years Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, called his People out of <hi>Babylon</hi> to build his Temple; before the Lord would accept of them into Covenant with himſelf, and to eat of the Paſſover, they with all other that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra 6. 21. Neh.</hi> 9. 1, 2, 3.</note> came with them, muſt ſeparate themſelves from all filthineſs of the Heathen of the Land: And among the many filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Heathen, which the Prieſt as well as others were defiled, was long hair. Now becauſe the Prieſts work was to teach the Lords People the difference between the Holy and Prophane, and cauſe them to diſcern between the Unclean <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 23.</note> and the Clean; and this they could not do, until themſelves were cleanſed from the ſame, namely from long hair, the ſhame to Mans Nature; and therefore the Command came firſt to them, namely to the Prieſt; as 'tis written, <hi>Neither ſhall they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſhave their heads, nor ſuffer their locks to grow long; they ſhall only poll their heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now why the Prieſt might not ſhave their head, becauſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num. 6. 9. Levit. 14 8, 9. Acts 21. 24. 1 Cor. 11. 15. Judg. 13. 5. 1 Sam. 1. 11. Deut.</hi> 17. 6.</note> that was commanded to the <hi>Nazarite</hi> and <hi>Lipers</hi> only, in their Cleanſings, as a Ceremonial Rite, now ended by Chriſt: nor might they ſuffer their locks to grow long, becauſe that was an effeminate badge, a ſhame to Mans Nature to wear; and alſo in ſuch Men as were born <hi>Nazarites,</hi> a ſign or figure for the time of their lives only; ſo that they muſt only poll their heads; and this is natural, agreeable to Gods Order in Nature, and agreeable in ſence with the word <hi>Shorn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus in the mouth of two Witneſſes, every Truth is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd: So then having proved both by the Apoſtle and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that the manner Man was created in reſpect of his hair; and that the Sons of <hi>Adam</hi> in all Ages were to wear their hair ſo, is according to the word of the Lord polled or ſhorn, as is manifeſt by the written word of God, when the Lord
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43039:10"/> called his People out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and now ſince the coming of Chriſt in the Fleſh, all that were called to become Members of the true Church of God, were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their hair, according to the word <hi>polled</hi> or <hi>ſhorn;</hi> that ſo in this thing they might be cleanſed from the filthineſs of <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11.</note> the Fleſh, according to the Moral Law. Now if there be any other Rule revealed, for Chriſtians to cut and wear their hair in theſe laſt days of the Goſpel, let it be made manifeſt by ſuch as do deny that their hair is not to be reformed by the Word of the Lord, polled or ſhorn: But that it is ſo to be reformed, is clear, elſe the Apoſtle would not have ſet Mans ſhort hair by the word <hi>Shorn,</hi> in oppoſition to Womans long hair, in theſe words: <hi>If the woman be not covered, let her</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 6.</note> 
               <hi>alſo be ſhorn:</hi> For who doth the Apoſtle mean by the word <hi>Alſo be ſhorn,</hi> but that as Man is to wear his hair ſhorn; ſo that he uſeth the word <hi>Shorn,</hi> by way of reproof to Woman for wearing her hair uncover'd; and therefore ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>If the woman be not covered, let her alſo be ſhorn,</hi> as Man was created, or ſhaven, as were the <hi>Nazarit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s; but if it be a ſhame for a woman to be ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en or ſhorn, let her he covered;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.</note> For if the woman be not covered, it is all one as if ſhe were ſhaven.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch then as all Sin is the breach of Gods Order, either in things Spiritual or Natural; and hereupon is that Royal Law divided into two Tables, that maketh Sin appear to be Sin: The firſt to make manifeſt, when in Worſhip any thing be done contrary to the firſt Table of Gods Law, it is ſin in matter or form; or any act or thing he done in Nature, contrary to the ſecond Table of Gods Law, it is ſin; ſo then as concerning things Natural, whatſoever Man or Woman is forbidden to wear, to wit, that which God hath given to woman as her natural covering, Man is forbid to covet or deſire; even ſo by the ſame Law, whatſoever Woman is forbidden to wear that pertains to Man, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ought not to deſire or covet: But Woman is forbidden to wear ſhort hair, becauſe it pertaineth to Man; therefore that Woman that coveteth or deſireth to wear her hair polled or ſhorn like unto Man, liveth in the breach of the Tenth Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhall not covet</hi>; is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 17.</note> guilty of the ſin of Covetouſneſs, in deſiring that thing that even Nature it ſelf teacheth, is a ſhame to her Nature to wear;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43039:11"/> ſo that it is not only a ſin againſt God, but a diſhonour to her Head, namely her Husband; even ſo that Man who deſireth <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 5.</note> or coveteth to wear his locks long, contrary to the Word of the Lord <hi>polled</hi> or <hi>ſhorn,</hi> breaketh Gods Order in Nature, and is guilty of the breach of the Tenth Commandment, in covering his head with the natural ſign of his Wifes ſubjection to him, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 4.</note> which is a ſin againſt God, in diſhonouring Chriſt his head, in deſpiſing the Image of God, in which he is created head of the Woman; and ſaith alſo, that he is not the glory of God; becauſe he, by wearing long hair, the ſign of Womans ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Man, ſaith he is no more in ſubjection to God than the Woman is, and that the Woman is not in ſubjection to Man her head, but equal in power with her Husband; and this is prov'd by the Apoſtle in theſe words: <hi>For a man indeed ought not to cover his head</hi> (that is, with long hair, Womans glory) <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 7.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe he is the image and glory of God:</hi> So then it is clear, that that Man that weareth long hair, the ſign of Womans ſubjection to Man, which is given to Woman to teach her ſhe is the glory of Man her Husband, ſaith, he is neither the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage nor glory of God: Even ſo that Woman that either cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth her hair ſhort, polled, or ſhorn, with its ends hanging out ſhort by the ears, and ſo ſtand ſtaring out on her forehead, ſaith ſhe is not the glory of the Man; or weareth her hair uucover'd, ſaith ſhe is not the glory of the Man, as aforeſaid: Now is this practice a light thing in Chriſtians, let the prudent judge.</p>
            <p>Moreover, what a higher degree of the breach of Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Nature, is it fit for Man to wear the very hair of Women, Womens natural covering, Womans glory, the very natural badge and ſign of Womans ſubjection to Man? Is not this a ſin of a high nature, in changing the natural uſe into that which is againſt Nature? And what is it that defileth Man but ſin? By it therefore perſons are unclean, ſo unfit to teach or partake of the holy thing of the Lord in his Church: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then that it was not lawful for Gods People of old to ſuffer their locks to grow long, much more unlawful to wear the long hair of Women, Womans garment, or Womans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural covering; for all that do ſo, were abomination to the <note place="margin">Deut. 22. 4.</note> Lord: And that theſe were not admitted into the Houſe or Temple of God of old for this ſin, and like open pollutions in Nature, is evident; for we read Porters were ſet at the Gate <note place="margin">2 Chrn. 23. 19.</note>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43039:11"/> of the Lords Houſe, that none that was unclean, or any thing might enter therein: And is it not ſo commanded under the Goſpel? The Porter is commanded to watch, and ſaith Chriſt the Lord, <hi>What I ſay unto one, I ſay unto all, Watch;</hi> to ſee <note place="margin">Mark 13. 34 Revel. 21. 27.</note> that there enter not into the City, or Goſpel Church, any thing that defileth or worketh abomination. Now then we have ſeen by the Word of the Lord, that they do work abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; to wit, even that Woman that weareth that which pertaineth to Man, to wit, ſhort hair, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that Man which putteth on, or weareth Womans natural covering, namely long hair, even the long hair of Women, becauſe that is Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans natural covering, as 'tis written, <hi>If a woman have long hair, it is a glory to her,</hi> (not to wear for ornament) but to <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 9.</note> teach her, although covered, ſhe is the glory of Man her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; <note place="margin">Numb. 6. 18.</note> ſo that that Man which weareth Womans natural co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, worketh abomination before the Lord; therefore ſuch are unclean, and were not fit to touch the holy things in the Church of God; even ſo it is now, for the Lord who is <note place="margin">Levit. 22. 1, 2, 3.</note> holy, requireth holineſs in the perſons of his People, becauſe they are the People of the Holy Ones; therefore the Lord will be ſanctified in all that draw near unto him in his ſervice; ſo that 'tis written, <hi>Be ye clean that bear the veſſells of the Lord:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4. 4. Iſai. 52. 11. John 15. 3</note> And hereupon the Lord gave ſtrict Laws upon pain of death to his People, that none in his uncleanneſs ſhould touch the holy things of the Church of God, foraſmuch as that was not only a defiling of the things themſelves, but of the Name <note place="margin">Levit. 22. v. 15, 2. 32. Jer. 15. 19.</note> of God alſo; ſo that if the Prieſt took not away the precious from the vile; they were not as Gods mouth, and broke Gods Law, and defiled the holy things, for which Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation was poured out againſt them, <hi>Ezek. 22. 26. 31.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſhall any perſwade themſelves, that that which is a ſhame to Mans Nature, and a ſin againſt God, in ſuch as wear long hair, or Womans long hair, doth it not defile the Man, ſeeing he breaketh Gods Order in Nature? If it had not been a ſin, and ſuch a ſin as was not to be ſuffered in any true Church of God, the Apoſtle would neither have blam'd the Men in the Church of God for wearing long hair, nor have told them, That if any ſeem to be contentious, as to plead a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his reproof he brought againſt Mens wearing of long <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 16.</note> hair, that they had no ſuch cuſtom, to wit, (as they were A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43039:12"/> and had care of all the Churches) to ſuffer it, namely, That Men under the profeſſion of Grace, ſhould walk in the ſhame to Nature; a practice never ſuffer'd in any true Church of God, in any Age of the World till this; and therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, we have no ſuch cuſtom to ſuffer it, neither the Church of God, if they walked with God in keeping his Commandments, becauſe God who is a God of Order, hath <note place="margin">Col. 2. 5.</note> joyn'd Order unto Faith, to be kept by all his People, being the two moſt reſpected things in the Churches of God; and why? becauſe <hi>without faith, none can pleaſe God;</hi> no more can <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 6.</note> the Works or Service done unto God, be accepted of the Lord, if not done according to his appointed Order: To give an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance herein. we read the Lord had given a plain Law concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the carrying of the Ark, the <hi>Levites</hi> were appointed to carry it upon their ſhoulders, but they muſt not touch it; the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieſt <note place="margin">1 Chron. 15. 2. Numb. 4.</note> might only touch it: But this Order was not obſerv'd when they carried the Ark in a Cart with Oxen: A <hi>Levite</hi> drove the Cart; when the Oxen ſtumbled, the <hi>Levite</hi> put forth his hand, out of a good intent to ſtay the Ark from falling, for which he was ſtruck dead: And hereupon King <hi>David</hi> with <hi>Iſrael</hi> lamented<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaying, <hi>The Lord our God made a breach upon us, for that we ſought him not after the due order:</hi> And <note place="margin">1 Chron. 15. 13.</note> was not the breach of Gods Order, one of the ruines of the Primitive Church? ſo how like is this day to that time, as the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> hath ſhewed the manner of the Apoſtacy how it began, even while the Apoſtles were living; to wit, firſt <note place="margin">Jude v. 3.</note> how few they were that contended for the Faith once give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Saints, the Faith of Gods Elect; ſo that Men ſpake evil of the true Doctrine of Faith, as it was the Faith of Jeſus; ſo Chriſt was deny'd in the works of Faith, and was in the name by many only profeſt, as 'tis written concerning ſuch, <hi>But theſe ſpeak evil of thoſe things which they know not;</hi> to wit, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <note place="margin">Jude v. 10.</note> of Faith, but what they know naturally as bruit Beaſts, in thoſe things they corrupt themſelves; ſo that they were <note place="margin">v. 11.</note> under this, <hi>Wo unto them, for they have gone in the way of</hi> Cain; to wit, in Self-righteouſneſs, expected to be accepted for the work done; and theſe ſaith <hi>Jude,</hi> ran greedily after the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Balaam</hi> for their Rewards; ſo that worldly gain was their Religion, or the chief end why they profeſt Chriſt in name only, and that theſe periſh'd in the gain-ſaying of <hi>Core,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43039:12"/> becauſe they deſpiſed Gods Order; for what was God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company, but becauſe they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded <note place="margin">Numb. 16.</note> to keep Gods Order in Service, which was the ruine of many of the Primitive Churches; the godly that took war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by what was written for all Churches Learning, how that the Lord made a breach on us, ſaid <hi>David,</hi> in killing <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi> for breaking Gods Order, although he did it with a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as aforeſaid; therefore the faithful ſuffering Chriſtians remembring, how ever after this, the Prophet <hi>David</hi> upon ſeeking the Lord, that he would aſſiſt him, that his ſteps <note place="margin">v. 7. 23. Pſal. 119. 133.</note> might be ordered in his word, as 'tis written, <hi>Look thou up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, and be merciful unto me, as thou uſeſt to do unto thoſe that love thy Name: Order my steps in thy word, and let not mine i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity have dominion over me:</hi> For becauſe 'tis again written, <hi>The ſteps of a good man, are ordered by the Lord, and he delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his way:</hi> So that he concludeth, <hi>To him that ordereth his converſation aright, or that diſpoſes his way,</hi> to wit, <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 23.</note> 
               <hi>to Gods word, will I ſhew the ſalvation of God.</hi> So then where Gods Order is not kept, there is no promiſe of a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; and therefore the Apoſtle after he had reproved ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things in the Church of God at <hi>Corinth,</hi> and had ſet them by his Counſel into a right order again, he commanded them ſaying, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi> Now then how undecent a thing 'tis written, <hi>Judge in your ſelves, is it comely for a woman to pray unto God,</hi> to wit, <hi>(with her hair uncovered) it is all one as if ſhe were ſhorn; but if it be a ſhame for a woman to be ſhorn or ſhaven, let her be covered.</hi> Again, to Man he ſaith, <hi>Doth not even nature it ſelf teach you, that if a man have long hair, it is a ſhame to him?</hi> Now then that which is ſhameful to a Man to do, is out of <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 14.</note> Gods Order; for Man was created ſo perfect in Nature, that there was not any thing, inwardly nor outwardly, whereof he might be aſhamed: So that if it be a ſhame for a Man to wear long hair, we are bound to believe Man was created with ſhort hair, and not with long hair; no not ſo long as in any ſence it could be made to ſerve to perform the end in the ſign. God in Creation gave Woman longhair, namely, for a ſign to teach her ſhe is the glory of Man her Husband; if them the Fall did no way abrogate Gods Order in Nature, but when
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43039:13"/> Man was reſtoed, together with the Woman, God giving them Faith to believe in Chriſt their Redeemer in the Word <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 8. Jude. v. 3. Gen. 3. 15.</note> of Promiſe, he joyn'd thereunto his Order, that they ſhould keep in his Service, and that by vertue of Creation; as 'tis written, <hi>Let the woman learn in ſil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce,</hi> to wit, in the Church, <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 12, 11.</note> 
               <hi>with all ſubjection:</hi> And again, <hi>But I ſuffer not a woman to teach, nor to uſurp authority over the man, but to be in ſilence:</hi> The Apoſtles reaſon is, from Gods Order in Creation; <hi>For</hi> 
               <note place="margin">v. 13, 14.</note> Adam <hi>was firſt form'd, then</hi> Eve: Adam <hi>was not deceived, but the woman being deceived, was in the tranſgreſſion; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſhe ſhall be ſav'd in child-bearing;</hi> that is, by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">John 8. 24. Act. 4. 14.</note> in her Seed Chriſt, for her Redeemer that ſhould be born of her, if they continued in that Faith <hi>(That the Seed of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 14. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Woman ſhould bruiſe the Serpents Head)</hi> and Charity or Love, (in keeping the Commandments of God) to wit, his holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in holineſs and ſobriety, and that Women adorn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in modeſt Apparel, with ſhame fac'dneſs and ſobriety; <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 9.</note> not with broidered Hair, or Gold, or Pearl, or coſtly Array, but, which becometh Women proſeſſing Godlineſs, with good Works.</p>
            <p>By this we ſee, that Gods Order in Nature muſt be kept' elſe Men and Women do not walk as they have received Chriſt, as 'tis written, <hi>For though I be abſent in the fleſh, yet</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>I am with you in the ſpirit, joyning and beholding your order, and the ſtedfaſtneſs of your faith in Chriſt.</hi> Thus to keep Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is a ſure way to keep Faith ſtedfaſt; for as Faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Works is dead, ſo is Faith without Order. Seeing then <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 26.</note> God hath joyn'd Order unto Faith, let no Man or Church put them aſunder, becauſe God hath joyn'd them together: But how do the Churches in this day put Faith and Order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder? not here to ſpeak of any thing but the Order of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. How is Order joyned unto Faith, ſo long as Men and Women break Gods Order, namely, in that Women cut their hair, ſhorn or polled, as Men ought to do; and Men do wear the long hair of Women on their head, to the ſhame of their Nature, diſhonour to God, and reproach to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>For hath not the Lord redeemed both Bodies and Souls of his People, and therefore will be glorified with both; and therefore the Perſon muſt firſt be accepted before his offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <note place="margin">3 Cor. 6. 20</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:43039:13"/> ring or ſervice can be; for ſo 'tis written, <hi>The Lord had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto</hi> Abel, <hi>and to his Offering; but unto</hi> Cain <hi>and to his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Offering he had not reſpect:</hi> How then' can the perſon of that Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be accepted of the Lord in his ſervice*, that preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his Perſon with Womans long hair on his head, Womens covering, Womans badge and ſign of Womans ſubjection to Man or his Head, whenas 'tis written, <hi>Every man praying or propheſying, having his head covered,</hi> to wit, with that which <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 4. Whenas the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to ſee their Kings diſhonour was not to be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Ezra 4. 14. 1 Sam. 2. 30.</note> is Womans natural covering, <hi>he diſhonoureth his head,</hi> to wit, <hi>Chriſt; for the head of the man is Chriſt:</hi> How can that Man be ſo deceived in himſelf, as to believe he can be accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſervice of God, whenas at that inſtance of time, in the Worſhip of God, he doth that act or thing which is a diſhonour to Chriſt his head: But that Man that weareth on his head a Womans covering, as Womans long hair is Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans covering, diſhonoureth Chriſt his head, therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be accepted of Chriſt in the worſhip of God; for what ſaith the Scripture, <hi>For them that honour me, I will honour; and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now is not Chriſt deſpiſed by Men that breaketh his Order in Nature? and is not this a horrible thing, when ſuch Men as are Miniſters of the Goſpel, who repreſents Chriſts Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Office in his Church; who are required before they may officiate in the Office of a Paſtor, that they be blameleſs? Now is this to be blameleſs in the ſervice of God, to come in <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 2.</note> the preſence of God with the forbidden thing on his head, whenas all things that are forbidden Men are unclean to them, and maketh Man unclean? Now if Men are told, In vain do <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 8, 9.</note> they worſhip God, teaching for Doctrines the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Men, ſurely in vain doth they worſhip God, that live in the breach of Gods Order in Nature.</p>
            <p>From whence then cometh long hair to be worn by Men, ſeeing 'tis not of God? We have ſeen it ſprang among the Heathens, as in <hi>Egypt,</hi> there <hi>Iſrael</hi> learnt it, as alſo to ſerve their Idols; but when they came out thence, they were clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">Levit. 18. 2, 3.</note> from both, and ever after charged, as 'tis written, <hi>No more to do after the manner of</hi> Egypt, <hi>wherein they dwelt, nor to do after the manner of</hi> Canaan, <hi>whither they were going,</hi> either in Worſhip or in Nature, contrary to the Table of Gods Law, which was added to the Covenant of Grace,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43039:14"/> when they came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> becauſe of tranſgreſſion, to make ſin to appear to be ſin, either in Worſhip, or in Nature, as theſe two Scriptures ſhew, <hi>Levit. 18. 2, 3. Dout. 22. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So likewiſe we have ſeen that the Lords People being ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years captive in old <hi>Babylon,</hi> learnt their ways; in wearing long hair therefore, they were corrupted, as well Prieſt as other, though not all; which when they came out, they were cleanſed from, as all that came with them, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the way to <hi>Sion,</hi> with their faces thitherward, ſaying, <hi>Come let us joyn our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetual Covenant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 50. 5. Heb. 13. 20.</note> (to wit, of Faith in Chriſt) <hi>that ſhall not be forgotten;</hi> ſo were they, as 'tis written, <hi>And the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>which were come again out of the Captivity, and all ſuch as had ſeparated</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezra 6. 21.</note> 
               <hi>themſelves unto them from the filthineſs of the Heathen of the Land, to ſeek the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>did eat,</hi> to wit, <hi>of the Paſſover:</hi> Then <hi>Iſrael</hi> was cleanſed, and their Veſſels ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified and made fit in holineſs, for the Lords uſe in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as 'tis written, <hi>Iſrael was holineſs to the Lord;</hi> and they <note place="margin">Jer. 2. 2.</note> were command ſo to be, as it is written not only to them then, but to the Goſpel-Churches, now by the ſame word, <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy;</hi> and therefore they muſt be ſeparated, and <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 16.</note> to touch no unclean thing (neither in Worſhip or in Nature) and then ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will receive you, and be a Father un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and ye ſhall be my Sons and Daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty.</hi> Having theſe Promiſes, ſaith the Apoſtle to the <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 16, 17, 18. 2 Cor. 11. 2. Jer. 2. 2, 3, Ezek. 16. 9. Exod. 19. 5. Iſai. 65. 23. 1 Cor. 7. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Corinthians,</hi> whom he reproved for being degenerated, in that they did among other things, walk in the ſhame to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, puts them in mind of their firſt ſtate, when eſpouſed to Chriſt, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was of old, as it is written to <hi>Iſrael, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thee, the kindneſs of thy youth, the love of thy Eſpouſal; when thou wenteſt after me in the wilderneſs.</hi> Iſrael <hi>was holineſs to the Lord; a holy Nation, a holy Seed, the bleſſed of the Lord, and their buds with them:</hi> Even ſo by the ſame Goſpel Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, the <hi>Corinthians</hi> and other Churches, were put in mind how they were eſpouſed to their Husband Chriſt; ſo were the Saints by calling <hi>a holy Nation, a holy Seed:</hi> and hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 9. 1. Cor. 1. 2.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle to them, when they were defiled in any thing, <hi>Let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 1. Pſal. 93. 5.</note> 
               <hi>perfecting holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> Seeing then Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs becometh the Lords dwelling-place; for where but two
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43039:14"/> or three are gathered together in his Name, he dwelleth <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 20.</note> there; ſo 'tis clear that long hair, the ſhame to Nature, muſt not, as it had not its original from God, abide in the City or true Church of God, who dwelleth there; no more now than of old; but as wickedneſs, it muſt as by the Wings of a Stork <note place="margin">Zach. 5. 8. 9, 10, 11.</note> by the cenſure of Gods word, be bore up between the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and the Earth, in the face of the Congregation, and be ſent from whence it took its original, into <hi>Babylon</hi> the Land of <hi>Shinar,</hi> into its own place: And as of old with which the ſpiritual <hi>Babylonians</hi> were ſpotted withal, ſo long hair was not the ſpots of the Lords People of old, no more now; but <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 5.</note> the ſpots of the Man of Sin, the bagde of ſpiritual <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon;</hi> which is the next thing in order to prove.</p>
            <p>We read in the Apoſtacy after the Apoſtles deceaſe, how <note place="margin">Rev. 6. 13. &amp; 1. 20. Jer. 17. 13.</note> many Stars or Miniſters of the Churches, together with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churches, fell away from the heavenly Profeſſion they once made of Chriſt, to an earthly, <hi>Whoſe God was their belly, whoſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 19.</note> 
               <hi>glory was their ſhame;</hi> for they minded earthly things. Now among the many Stars, there was one who ſtrove for prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence; <note place="margin">3 John. v. 9.</note> and God ſuffered it ſo to be, as a plague to the World, that refuſed his Son for their Saviour: unto whom was <note place="margin">Luke 11. 52. Rev. 9. 1. 2 Theſ. 2. 11.</note> given a Key not of true ſaving Knowledge, but of ſtrong Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; by which he opened a bottomleſs pit, out of which pit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe a great ſmoak as the ſmoak of a Furnace, ſo powerful were his Errour and Hereſie, which he managed according to fleſhly Wiſdom, which is ſaid to come from beneath, ſo <note place="margin">Jam. 3. 15.</note> not of God from above; therefore it is earthly, ſenſual, and deviliſh: By reaſon hereof the Sun and Air, to wit, the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of the Goſpel, was ſo darkened from the true light, as it ſhined according to the teaching of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; and alſo the Moral Law was corrupted from the true ſence and meaning thereof, as it had been opened and explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which may likened to the Air, or leſſer light in Nature, as the effects doth prove; for as touching true Faith, the Followers, the Worſhippers of the Beaſt, were deſtitute of; ſo were they likened to cruel and <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3. 2. Mat. 3. 7. Rev. 9. 5.</note> unreaſonable Creatures, a Generation of Vipers and Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions for cruelty, as the Apoſtle hath taught, <hi>The Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me from unreaſonable men, for all men have not faith:</hi> Even ſo the light in Nature was ſo darkened, in that they had ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43039:15"/> hermaphrodited themſelves into a monſtrous ſhape, that they ſaw it's no ſhame to wear a womaniſh length of hair, the ſhame to Mans Nature, as it is written, <hi>And their faces were as the faces of men, and they had hair as the hair of women:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 9. 7. 8.</note> By this we ſee how the old <hi>Egypt,</hi> and old <hi>Babylon,</hi> were Types in all manner of wickedneſs of the ſpiritual <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> ſo that long hair had its original out of the bottomleſs pit, even from Hell it ſelf; ſo that in a double reſpect, it was charged upon them to be abominable; firſt, as long hair in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men is a ſign of their ſubjection to their Head or Husband, ſo long hair in the Subjects of Antichriſt, proved them the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Man of Sin. 2. As the Man of Sin, together with all his Members, make one Body; ſo the Member of the Beaſts, as the Member of a Man, they were ſo deformed by, and in all diſorder in Nature, as alſo in Worſhip, that they were like to Men-monſters, having faces as the faces of Men, and hair as the hair of Women; and that the Nation were over ſpread with this unnatural guiſe, until the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt of this Nation, as ſhall anon appear.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the Lord never left himſelf without Witneſſes in the worſt of times; namely, his ſealed ones, who had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <note place="margin">Rev. 7. 2.</note> Seal of their Election, to wit, in departing from all iniquity, as it is written, <hi>The foundation of God ſtandeth ſure:</hi> Having <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 19.</note> this Seal, the Lord knoweth them that are his; <hi>Let every one that nameth the name of Jeſus, depart from iniquity:</hi> Theſe are the called, choſen, and faithful ones, which received the love <note place="margin">Rev. 17. 14.</note> of the Truth, who in that heavenly Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> are likened to a Woman a wonder to the World, having the Sun for her cloathing, the Moon for her footſtool, and on <note place="margin">Rev. 12. 1, 2.</note> her head a Crown of twelve Stars, while ſhe by Faith and Holineſs had put on Chriſt, as ſhe had learned him of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, ſo was ſhe advanced to heavenly Dignity; her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation being in Heaven, ſo loved ſhe no more this World, <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 14. 2 Tim. 3. 14. Phil. 3. 20. Rev. 12. 17.</note> of whom herſelf is not, therefore the World hateth her and perſecuteth her, and why, as it is written, <hi>The Dragon was wrath with the Woman, and went to make war with the remnant of her ſeed which kept the Commandments, and have the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Jeſus.</hi> And again, <hi>Here is the patience of the Saints; here are they that keep the Commandments of God, and the faith of Jeſus: Theſe are they which were not defiled with Women,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43039:15"/> 
               <hi>for they are Virgins,</hi> abiding faithful from the day, even as when they joyn'd themſelves to the Lord, by entring into Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the Lord Jeſus; then were they ſaid to he as a chaſte Virgin, eſpouſed to Chriſt their Husband; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Jer. 2. 2. 2 Cor. 11. 1, 2. Rev. 14. 4, 5.</note> 'tis ſaid of them again, <hi>They are Virgins; theſe are they that follow the Lamb whitherſover he goeth; and in their mouth was found no guile; for they were without fault before the Throne of God;</hi> to wit, in the true Church of God, in the Kingdom of Chriſts Mediatorſhip, where the Lord Jeſus, King of Saints, fitteth on his Throne, their King and Prieſt, to order it, and <note place="margin">Rev. 15. 3. Zac. 6. 13. Iſai. 9. 7.</note> to eſtabliſh it with Judgment and Juſtice, from henceforth and for evermore: And thus we ſee where Order is joyned unto Faith, here are they that keep the Commandments of God, and have the Faith of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Theſe things duly weighed, we may clearly ſee how that the ſuffering Chriſtians in all Ages, ſince the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, for the ſpace of theſe ſixteen hundred years, who are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of in that Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> are juſtified by the Spirit of <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 5.</note> God, to be without fault before the Throne of God; ſo that if they had been guilty, either of errour in Faith, or the breach of Gods Order in Worſhip, or in Nature, they would not have been proclaimed Juſt; for the Spirit of God, the <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 18.</note> faithful and true Witneſs that cannot lye, is not Yea and Nay, but Yea and Amen: For when the Church or Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God joyned Order unto Faith, then they have this praiſe, I joy and rejoyce to behold your Order and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs <note place="margin">Col. 2. 5.</note> of your Faith in Chriſt; but when Order is broken, we ſee the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> and others was reproved; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſuffering Chriſtians were not taxed with the breach of <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> any one of the Commandments of God, but are commended. <hi>Well done good and faithful Servant,</hi> as aforeſaid: Here are <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 12. Mat. 25. 23. 1 Eheſ. 1. 3.</note> they that keep the Commandment of God, and have the Faith of Jeſus: Thus Order was by them joyned unto Faith; for to believe is the work of Faith, and to keep the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God is the labour of love, keeping Gods holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Grace and Nature. Another Seal of our Election, as the Apoſtle hath taught, ſaying, <hi>Making mention of you in our prayer, remembring without ceaſing your work of faith and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> 
               <note place="margin">v. 4. 21.</note> 
               <hi>of love and patience, I hope in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in the fight of God our Father, knowing Brethren beloved, your election</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:43039:16"/> 
               <hi>of God.</hi> By all which we ſee, that not ſo much as the Order of God in this one point in Nature, was broken by the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chriſtians for theſe ſixteen hundred years paſt, no not in Mens wearing of long hair, the ſhame to Mans Nature: And for further confirmation hereof, we have the Teſtimony of Men who have, as is judged, faithfully collected the Truth, in what they believed and maintained to their Deaths; but alſo have drawn the form of the ſuffering Chriſtians, as they wear their hair, when they ſuffered death. Now then let the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial eye ſee the form or effigies of the ſuffering Chriſtians, in the Book of Martyrs, and elſewhere; and then judge whether they do believe when the Chriſtians were living, any could have made their hair to ſerve for a covering of their eyes, by drawing it forward, much leſs the face and all: So that long hair is not the ſpots of the Lords People in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges paſt, but the ſpots of the Apoſtate Chriſtians, as 'tis ſhewed before: Neither is it the ſpots of the Lords People, now if they keep themſelves in their garments or covering on their head unſpotted from the fleſh; then could it not of them be ſaid, that they have <hi>faces of men, and hair as the hair of women;</hi> that is, ſo long hair, that by drawing it forward, it could be made to ſerve to perform the end in the ſign, for which God in Creation, and ſo in Nature, gave Woman long hair for; namely, for a covering to cover the eyes, as aforeſaid: So then we ſee as long hair is a ſign in Nature of Womans ſubjection to Man, which the Apoſtrate Chriſtians were not only polluted withal, but alſo from the end in the ſign, as by a borrowed ſpeech, they were charged to be the ſubject of the Man of Sin, <hi>Apollion</hi> their head, <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 9. 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>faces of men, and hair as the hair of women.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And will not the Chriſtian Churches in this day conſider theſe things, that long hair in Men is a ſign of ſubjection to the Man of Sin; and therefore is ſo inſufferable a thing to be worn by Men in the Churches of God: And where doth the fault chiefly lie, that this diſorder is ſuffered, that Chriſt is therein diſhonoured in the Churches in this day, even at the Miniſters door, becauſe they ſhun to declare all the <note place="margin">Act. 20. 27. Rom. 15. 4. 1 Cor. 10. 11.</note> Counſel of God, to warn the People concerning this Sin. For to what end did the Lord give the Law to <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they came out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> and ſtill 'tis written for our Learning and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43039:16"/> Admonition, on whom the ends of the World is come: That <note place="margin">Deut. 22. 4.</note> a Woman ſhall not wear that which pertaineth to Men, one thing eſpecially is ſhort hair; and neither ſhall a Man put on a Womans garment or natural covering, one thing in ſpecial is Womans long hair, Womans natural covering: And to what end did the Lord give the Law, when his People came out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> buf to teach us as them, that Men ſhould not <note place="margin">Ezek. 44. 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſhave their heads, nor ſuffer their locks to grow long, but only poll their heads.</hi> And is it not a perpetual Rule to warn Men, they ſhall not break Gods Order in this thing in Nature, and to take off all excuſe that ſome have made, when told of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring long hair, by the words of the Apoſtle? <hi>Doth not even Nature it ſelf teach you, if a man have long hair, 'tis a ſhame to him?</hi> Yea, but ſay ſome, how long muſt Mans hair be, when <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 14.</note> Nature it ſelf teacheth, 'tis a ſhame to Man to wear? We ſee the Objection is anſwered by the Lord himſelf, <hi>They ſhall only poll their heads,</hi> and not ſuffer the locks to grow long. Now, as aforeſaid, ſeeing Womans hair is called long when it will cover her eyes, becauſe it will then perform the end in the ſign God gave Woman long hair for, to teach her ſubjection to Man her Husband, the covering of her eyes; therefore for Man to wear that length of hair that will perform the Female ſign, to wit, that will cover the eyes, is againſt Mans Nature to wear, being the ſign of the Wifes ſubjection to Man her head. And thus even Nature it ſelf teacheth, it is a ſhame for Man to have long hair; ſo then the word <hi>ſhorn</hi> or <hi>polled,</hi> is to cut out the womaniſh length of hair, a covering to her eyes, and then it will not bear the name Long hair. And thus all the ſuffering Chriſtians, both Miniſters and other, by their practice underſtood the word <hi>Poll</hi> or <hi>Shorn,</hi> to cut their hair ſhort, that it could not be made by drawing it forward to cover their eyes, is evident: If this be not the true ſence and meaning of the words, let the courteous-minded ſpeak and prove by Scripture, what other Rule there is then accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word <hi>polled</hi> or <hi>ſhorn,</hi> for Men to cut their hair by, and ſo to wear it.</p>
            <p>If then the ſin lieth at the Miniſters door, becauſe they do not teach the People their Duty in this thing, as the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the Ages paſt did, by example of the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: What then is the reaſon they do not teach againſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43039:17"/> Mens wearing of long hair, or the wearing the long hair of Women, becauſe they themſelves are chief Treſpaſſers in this evil thing; for if they ſhould teach againſt it, they ſhould openly condemn themſelves, although their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences beareth witneſs in them that they do evil, unleſs the Conſcience be ſo fear'd, as were ſome of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who taught others the Duty of the Moral Law, and had not taught them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; therefore the Apoſtle reproved thoſe Teachers by the very Heathen, as 'tis written, <hi>For when the Gentiles which</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 21.</note> 
               <hi>have not the Law, do by nature the things contained in the Law; theſe having not the Law, are a Law unto themſelves, which ſhew the works of the Law written in their hearts, their Conſcience alſo bearing witneſs, and their thoughts the mean while accuſing or excuſing one another: Behold thou art called a Jew, or behold thou art called a Chriſtian, and reſteſt in the Law, and makeſt thy boaſt of God, and knoweſt his will and approveſt the things that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 29. Rev. 2. 9. Rom. 2. 17. 18, 19, 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>are more excellent, being instructed out of the Law, and art confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that thou thy ſelf art a guide to the blind, a light of them that are in darkneſs, an inſtructer of the fooliſh, a teacher of babes, which haſt the form of knowledge and truth in the Law: Thou therefore which teachcſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf? Thou that prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt a man ſhall not ſteal, doſt thou ſteal? Thou that makeſt thy boaſt of the Law, through breaking the Law diſhonoureſt thou God.</hi> Now then whatſoever Man or Woman doth againſt Nature, <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 1 Cor. 11. 14.</note> is a breach of the Moral Law; but for a Man to wear his own locks long, is againſt Mans Nature, therefore a breach of the tenth Commandment, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet,</hi> to wit, the forbidden thing; but Womans long hair is Womans cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, therefore is forbidden Man to wear; therefore for a <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 13. Deut. 22. 4 Jam. 2. 10.</note> Man to covet that God hath forbidden Man, is ſin, as 'tis written, <hi>A man ſhall not put on a womans garment, or natural covering.</hi> Now hear what the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all.</hi> What need had every Chriſtian, eſpecially eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Goſpel-Miniſter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſee-that they walk circumſpectly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they muſt not teach the People in words only, but in purity in all their actions, as 'tis written, <hi>Be thou an example to the believers, in word, in converſation, in charity, or love, in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſpirit, in faith, in purity; for as dead flyes cauſe the ointment of the Apothecary to ſend forth a ſtinking ſavour; ſo doth a little</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 10. 1.</note>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:43039:17"/> 
               <hi>folly him that is in reputation for wiſdom and honour.</hi> For are <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 9.</note> not Men by the Churches of God choſen into Office, becauſe they excell others in the Word of God; and when they Rule well, they are worthy of double honour, not only to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd of for the Works ſake, but care to be taken to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 17.</note> them: But when they give an evil example to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in wearing on their heads the forbidden thing, the long hair of Women, Womans natural covering, with which, ſaith the Apoſtle, indeed <hi>a man ought not to cover his head;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis Womans glory, but Mans ſhame, they diſhonour God, ſo it is folly and ſhame to them, becauſe Man is the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and glory of God, but the Woman is the glory of the Man; long hair being Womans glory for a ſign thereof, is therefore a ſhame to Mans nature to wear, and more eſpecially a ſhame to the Miniſters of the Goſpel, that ſhould (as 'tis written) approve themſelves among other things, to be the Miniſters of Chriſt by pureneſs; for are they not in the trial <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 6</note> of them when to be judged fit for the Miniſtry, to be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs? Surely Men cannot be blameleſs, when they do that <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 2.</note> thing that is by the Doctrine of the New Teſtament, a ſhame to Mans Nature: yea, how do ſuch Men abſtain from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evil, that are charged to walk in the ſhame to Nature? For ſurely had not long hair worn by Men been a <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 22.</note> ſin, the Apoſtle would not have blamed the Church of God for ſuffering ſuch an evil practice among them: Yea' how can ſuch Miniſter that give the People ſo evil example, in wearing the long hair of Women on their heads, be accounted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of any honour or eſteem from the People, becauſe of <note place="margin">2 Tim. 5. 17.</note> their evil practice herein? Or how are ſuch Miniſters worthy of the honour, as to have care taken for them, in providing maintenance to keep them and their Families? whenas in this thing in wearing long hair, it may be juſtly complained of them as of old, <hi>The leader of the people cauſe them to err, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 9 16. Lam. 2. 14.</note> 
               <hi>they that are led by them, are destroyed.</hi> And again, <hi>Thy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets or Teachers have ſeen vain and fooliſh things; for thee they have not diſcovered their Iniquity, to turn away thy Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, but have ſeen for their falſe Burdens and cauſes of Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> For theſe things, Judgment muſt begin at the Houſe <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 17.</note> of God, if ſins be ſuffered there; therefore it was and ſtill is commanded all the Lords Miniſters to cry aloud, <hi>Spare not, ſet</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 58. 1.</note>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:43039:18"/> 
               <hi>the Trumpet to thy mouth, ſhew the Lords people their ſin and tranſgreſſion.</hi> But when the Watch-men do not diſcharge their Duty herein, then the Lord diſcovered what a wretched condition they were in, whenas they thought themſelves in a good condition, pampering their Bodies, as 'tis written, <hi>Come</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 56. 10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>ye, ſay they, I will fetch wine, and we will fill our ſelves with ſtrong drink; and to morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us hear the Lords Meſſage ſent to theſe Belly. Gods, <hi>Whoſe God is their belly, whoſe glory is their ſhame,</hi> becauſe they ſeek or love earthly things, more than the Souls good of their Flocks, as 'tis written, <hi>His watch-men are all blind, they are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 26. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>all ignorant; they are all dumb dogs, they cannot bark, ſleeping, lying down, loving to ſlumber. Yea, they are greedy dogs which can never have enough; they are ſhepherds that cannot underſtand, they look to their to own way, every one for his gain from his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if this look too like the day we are fallen into, then that we may not judge amiſs <hi>Every tres is known by its fruit;</hi> but <note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> ſurely that is not good fruit which is a ſhame to Mans nature to bring forth or bear, but the long hair of Women is a ſhame to Mans nature, therefore not good fruit for the Trees of Righteouſneſs to bear: what then is another the cauſe the <note place="margin">Iſai. 61. 3.</note> Miniſter do not reprove this ſin that is an open ſhame? Is it becauſe the Rich in the Congregation are generally moſt guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 2, 3, 4. Iſai. 56. 11.</note> and they are not willing to diſpleaſe them, leſt they loſe their gain from their quarterly payments they receive from them; and it is becauſe they ſhould leſſen their Congregation: for 'tis to be feared many glory more in their number, than in taking care to ſee their Flock walk as becometh the Goſpel, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 31.</note> as the Apoſtle hath ſaid, <hi>He that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord;</hi> to know as he is holy, ſo his People: The Flock of Holineſs are commanded to be holy in all manner of Coverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo ought every true Paſtor to be diligent to know the <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 23.</note> ſtate of his or rather Chriſts Flock: For to what end are Men choſen to be Miniſters, but as eyes to ſee good things for the Peoples Souls, as they are to provide food and cloathing for their Bodies and their Families. See what the Lord ſaith of old, <hi>If the people of the Land take a man of their Coast, and ſet him</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 33. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>for their watch-man; if the watch-man ſee the Sword come, and</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:43039:18"/> 
               <hi>blow not the Trumpet, and the people be not warned; iſ the Sword come and take away any perſon from among them, he is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in his iniquity; but his bloud will I require at the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hands.</hi> To this it ſeemeth the Apoſtle may have refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, with reſpect to his charge he had over all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as Apoſtolical Watch-man: Whereas this care and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is branched forth to particular Paſtors or Watch-men in their particular charge; not as Apoſtles, but Watch-men over the particular Flock they are ſet Overſeers to; as the Elders of <hi>Epheſus</hi> had particular charge to that Church only; to whom he advertiſeth, as they had taken charge of them, they ſhould take the Apoſtle for their example, who had a care of all the Churches; ſo that this was his comfort, as 'tis written in his words, <hi>To the Elders of the Church of God at</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus; <note place="margin">Act. 20. 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>I take you to record this day, that I am pure from the bloud of all men:</hi> His reaſon is; <hi>For I have not ſhunned, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto you all the Counſel of God; take heed therefore to your</hi> 
               <note place="margin">v. 18.</note> 
               <hi>ſelves,</hi> to wit, <hi>that you fulfil your Miniſters, as others are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 4. 17.</note> 
               <hi>that you have received in the Lord, that you fulfil it faithfully, in declaring the whole Counſel of God; ſo that ye like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 2.</note> 
               <hi>may be free from the bloud of all men; you have taken care and charge to feed, to reprove, to rebuke, to ſee that every one do</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 5. 1 Cor. 14. 40.</note> 
               <hi>their work and duty, and that order be joyn'd unto faith; ſo that all things be done decently and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then it is every true Miniſters duty to declare as there is time and opportunity, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, the whole Counſel of God; a part of which is to reprove that ſinful ſhame of Mens wearing of long hair; yea, alſo the long hair of Women, becauſe it is ſin; for what one ſin lived in, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth not death, temporal and eternal? So then if the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter do not declare the whole Counſel of God, according to his written Word, and the People live in ſin. If any are taken away in his ſin, his Bloud God will require at the Watch mans hand: By this we ſee why Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 33. 6. John 20.</note> ſo often, <hi>Loveſt thou me? feed my ſheep, feed my ſheep, feed my ſheep:</hi> this is the Paſtors duty and love to Chriſt; the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect is both a hating of Chriſt, and the Souls he hath taken charge of, as 'tis written, <hi>Be thou diligent to know the ſtate of thy flock, and look well to thy hards: Thou ſhalt not hate thy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Brother in thine heart, thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43039:19"/> and not ſuſſer ſin upon him, leſt thou bear ſin for him:</hi> And not only concerning a Brother is this care to be taken, but if <note place="margin">Lev. 19. 17. Mat. 18.</note> the whole Church do ſin in doing any thing againſt any of the Commandments of the Lord, concerning things which ſhould not be done, and are guilty, the whole Church muſt repent thereof unto the Lord; and to that end are the Faithful to <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2. 1, 2. Rev. 3. 4.</note> plead with their Mother, as the few Names in <hi>Sardis</hi> did, having the Faithful in <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their example.</p>
            <p>Now conſider, whether the ſinful ſhame to Mans Nature, to wit, Men in wearing long hair, yea, the long hair of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; and Women wearing their hair ſhorn or polled, be not an abomination to the Lord, whenas God created Man polled or ſhorn, in reſpect of his hair, and commanded him ſo to keep and wear it: And Woman was created with long hair, and is charged ſhe ſhall not cut or wear her hair like to Man: But on the clean contrary, Men wear Womans long hair, and Women wear ſhort hair; and this is ſuffered in almoſt every Congregation that ſay they are the Churches of God. Now what is this but ſuch a ſin, yea, of a high nature, reckoned among the moſt grievous ſins, but becauſe 'tis ſuch a ſin where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Men and Women have changed the natural uſe, into that which is againſt Nature? A ſin of that nature, never heard of to be ſuffered in any true Church of God; and that this ſin is ſo generally ſpread, that it is as a Leproſſe, which if not ſpeedily reformed and removed out of the Church, the Lord will now as of old, <hi>Abhor the excellency of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and hate his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amos 6. 9. Exek. 9. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Palaces for the wickedneſs of their inventions;</hi> as it is written, <hi>I will caſt them out of my houſe, I will love them no more.</hi> And to them that mourn in the Churches, to ſee theſe as like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abominations, and have uſed means to have it redreſſed, and it is not reformed, they are commanded to come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and touch not the unclean thing, and the Lord will receive them, and be a Father to them, and they ſhall be <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 16, 17.</note> his Sons and Daughters: <hi>Theſe ſhall find more comfort with a dinner of herbs, where love is to God and their Neighbour, than a stalled Oxe and hatred therewith;</hi> for of ſuch 'tis written, <note place="margin">Prov. 15. 17. Mal. 9. 3. Mat. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another, and a Book of remembrance was written for them that thought on his name:</hi> For where if but two or three are gathered together in his Name, he will be in the midſt of them to bleſs them;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43039:19"/> that whoſoever toucheth them, toucheth the Apple of his <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 2. Pſal. 50. 16. Rev. 3. 4. Exod. 23. 2. Pſal. 26. 5.</note> Eye: To all other the Lord ſaith, <hi>What haſt thou to do to take my Word into thy mouth, that hateſt to be reformed.</hi> So then it is the few Names that walk with Chriſt in white, for they are worthy that obey the voice of the Lord; as 'tis written, <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to do evil;</hi> and with <hi>David,</hi> do hate the Congregation of evil dores, and will not ſit with the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for though hand joyn in hand, the wicked ſhall not be unpuniſhed.</p>
            <p>By all which it appeareth, that as in the Apoſtacy after the Apoſtles deceaſe, the ſin was chiefly in the Stars or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that fell from their heavenly profeſſion to an earthly, whereby all diſorder was countenanced; ſo that the godly which departed from the evil, make themſelves a prey; yet the trial of their Faith was more precious than gold: for we have ſeen how the ſuffering Chriſtians were as Lights in the <note place="margin">Rev. 12. 1. Prov. 4. 18. Dan. 12. 3. Phil. 2. 15. prov. 5. 22.</note> World; who rather ſhined more unto the perfect day, when other that wandred after the Beaſt, were in the Kingdom of Darkneſs, holden with the cords of their own ſin; ſo that the Sun and Air was darkened in them, that they ſaw it no ſhame, as in the Apoſtacy in this day no Men ſee it no ſhame for to <hi>have faces as the faces of men, and hair as the hair of women:</hi> However it pleaſed God, by means of the godly aforementioned, to wit, the ſuffering Chriſtians, whoſe paths ſhineth as aforeſaid, more and more unto the perfect day; that when the Nations were overſpread in Mens wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring long hair, the ſhame to Nature, <hi>Theophilus</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Prinn <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comlineſs of long locks,</hi> p. 11. <hi>Mr.</hi> Speed <hi>Hiſtory of Great</hi> Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, <hi>l. 9. c. 4. numb. 54. p. 44. 2.</hi>
               </note> as Writers ſay, enacted a Law that all Men ſhould cut their hair ſhort; and that no <hi>Roman</hi> ſhould ſuffer it to grow below his neck: The like did King <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt of this Nation, who commanded that Men ſhould cut their hair ſhort in this Nation; and no doubt the King himſelf gave his Subjects a good example, together with the Chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and likewiſe the Teachers of the People in that day: ſo that there was a general Reformation in Mens cutting and wearing their hair polled or ſhorn, according to the Command of the King of Kings, as afore-ſhewed; and this Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on continued in this Nation for near five hundred years, until <note place="margin">Ezek. 44. 20. 1 Cor. 11. 6, 14.</note> the latter end of the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt; ſo that ſome yet alive can remember, if a Malefactor was brought
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43039:20"/> before a Judge at Aſſize, or Juſtices at Seſſions, if he had long hair, they commanded it to be cut off; ſo careful were all Magiſtrates and Fathers, and Maſters in Families, to ſee both old and young Men, even to the Children, that they had their hair cut ſhort: So likewiſe all the Reformed Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Churches were ſo careful, that they would not admit a Member to be joyned to them, iſ his hair was not according to Gods Order, polled or ſhorn: So that if the Churches look not to ſee the Moral Law kept, as well as the Law of Faith rightly believed, the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> tells us, <hi>What doth it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 14.</note> 
               <hi>my br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thren, though a man ſay he hath faith, and have not works; can his faith ſave him.</hi> Now to reſpect perſons in the way of Faith is a breach of the Moral Law; how much more for a Man to do that act that is not only a ſhame to Mans Nature, but a great diſhonour to the Lord our Creator, afore ſhewed, in Mens wearing long hair? Moreover, how many Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v. 2. 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> had the Church of God at <hi>Epheſus?</hi> and yet wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the root Faith that worketh by Love; for which the Lord threatned to remove her Candleſtick, except ſhe repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and did her firſt Work. Now as Faith is to Believe, ſo Love is to Obey; and hereupon Chriſt hath taught, <hi>If a man love me, he will keep my words; but he that lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th me not, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 14. 23. v. 24.</note> 
               <hi>not my ſayings.</hi> This was the great ſin in the Church of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> the keeping of the Commands of Chriſt was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected; ſo was ſhe charged to have forſaken her firſt Love, the Love of her Eſpouſal, in the day they by Covenant were Eſpouſed or Married to Chriſt their head; the Agreement <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 32. Deut. 26. 16, 17, 18. 2 Cor. 11. 2. Rev. 19. 7, 8, 9. Jer. 50. 5.</note> was, as it is written of old, <hi>Thou haſt avouched the Lord to be thy God, and to walk in his way, and to keep his Statutes and Commandments, and to bearken unto his voice; and the Lord hath avouched thee this day to be his peculiar People, as he hath promiſed thee, and that thou ſhouldſt keep all his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> The breach of this Covenant made in Chriſt, was the reaſon the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> Candleſtick was threatned to be removed, as it is written to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ro wit, <hi>Judah</hi> of old, <hi>Their root ſhall be rottenneſs, and their bloſſom ſhall go up as the duſt, becauſe they have caſt away the Law of the Lord, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the Word of the holy one of</hi> Iſrael. <note place="margin">Iſai. 5. 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now then if as the Apoſtle hath taught, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 10.</note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43039:20"/> And is not one point of the Law of God, that Men ſhall not ſuffer their locks to grow long? Hear what the Scripture ſaith, when Gods People of old were told of their evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and would not hear, then they that were yeſterday Gods <note place="margin">Mica 2. 8.</note> People, are ſaid to be riſſen as an Enemy, when they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to obey him: Now what ſaith Chriſt the Lord to ſuch, <hi>Bring thoſe mine enemies that would not that I ſhould</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 19. 7, 14. Matth. 21. 43. John 15. 14.</note> 
               <hi>reign over them, and ſlay them before me; yea, the Kingdom ſhall be taken from them, and given to a people bringing forth the fruit thereof: for ye are my friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then what was the vain boaſting of the <hi>Jews,</hi> in their half keeping the Commands of God? as it is written, <note place="margin">Hoſ. 12. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Ephraim ſaid, I am become rich, I have found me out ſubstance; for in all my labours, they ſhall find no iniquity in me;</hi> when at that time they were charged to be without the true God, without teaching Prieſt, and without Law; even ſo the Church of the <hi>Leodiceans</hi> boaſted, <hi>I am rich and increaſed with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 15. 3.</note> 
               <hi>goods, and have need of nothing:</hi> At which time he was wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, miſerable, poor, blind, and naked, when ſhe had only <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 17. Zac. 11. 5. Prov. 13. 1.</note> the outward gifts left, as Preaching and Praying, which God giveth to very Hypocrites: But love to God in keeping his Commandments, was not by her regarded. Hear what the Apoſtle ſaith to ſuch a Church-ſtate: <hi>Though I ſpeak with the tongue of Men and Angels, and have not love, I am become a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſounding braſs and tinkling ſymbal: though I have the gift of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy and of under ſtanding, all myſteries and all knowledge, and though I have all faith, ſo that I could remove mountains, and have not love, I am nothing; and though I give all my goods to feed the poor, and my body to be burned, and have not love, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth me nothing.</hi> So then <hi>it is not every one that ſaith Lord,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, ſhall enter into the King dom of Heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father that is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I'll appeal to the Conſcience of the Miniſters in this day, whether it be not the Will of God, that Men ſhall wear their hair polled or ſhorn; and whether it he not againſt the Will of God, that Men ſhould wear either their own locks long, or the locks of Women: Now this having been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo great a ſin, what have the Faithful to do, that mourn to ſee this abomination ſo overſpread in the Churches of God.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43039:21"/> to call upon their Miniſters to juſtifie the practiſe of Mens weariag the long hair of Women in Periwigs, as to bear their Teſtimony by preaching againſt it; and that all that will not be reformed, todeal with them according to Gods holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as it is written, <hi>If thy brother ſin, tell him of his fault; if</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 15, 16, 17. Gal. 6. 1, 2. Jame. 5. 16. Lev. 19. 17. Rev. 22. 14.</note> 
               <hi>he hear thee, thou haſt gained thy brother; if he refuſe, to take one or two and admoniſh him; if he hear not them, to tell it to the Church, that ſo the Church may admoniſh him: if he refuſe to hear the Church, to caſt him out;</hi> foraſmuch as none have right to the Tree of Life, but thoſe that keep the Commandments of God: See and read the Scriptures in the Margin. But if the Miniſter with the greateſt part, do ſtand to juſtifie this or any other evil practiſe, then the ſealed ones marked of God, to be ſaved from the deſtruction when the multitude will perſiſt <note place="margin">Ezek. 9. 4. Hoſ. 2. 1, 2. Iſai. 66. 5. John 9. 34. Mal. 3. 16.</note> in evil, muſt plead with their Mother, plead that ſhe no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger remaineth the Wiſe of Chriſt than ſhe is obedient to all his Commands, though they are caſt out; as it is written, <hi>Your brethren that hated you, that caſt you out for my name ſake; then theſe that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to another, and the Lord hearkned and heard it, and a book of remembrance was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before him, -for them that feared the Lord and thought upon his Name; and they ſhall be mine, ye they ſhall walk with m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in white, for they are worthy.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Again, one might be aſtoniſhed with <hi>Daniel</hi> for an hour, to <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 19.</note> conſider that ever Chriſtians, after ſixteen hundred years practiſe of all the ſuffering Chriſtians, and five hundred years of that time of this whole Nations, wearing their hair accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word of the Lord, polled or ſhorn, as the ancient Effigies of the Nobility and Gentry and others do ſhew, that ever Men ſhould be ſo bereaved of the ſence of Nature, to be drawn in by the policy of Satan to wear long hair, ye and the Miniſters of the Goſpel alſo, when if the eye is evil, the whole body is full of darkneſs.</p>
            <p>We read in a Book publiſhed in the Year 1628. intituled, <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlovelineſs of Love-locks;</hi> in the fifth page it is ſaid that a late Learned Hiſtorian informeth us, that the manner of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>By Mr.</hi> Pinn <hi>Eſq; Mr.</hi> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas <hi>Pilgr.</hi> l. 8. c. 6. ſect. 3.</note> the <hi>Virginians</hi> was to wear a long lock on the left ſide their heads, in imitation of their Devil-God, whom they called <hi>Ocbeus;</hi> whence it was that a <hi>Virginian</hi> coming into <hi>England,</hi> blamed <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men for not wearing a long lock as they did,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43039:21"/> affirming our God was not the true God, becauſe he had no Love lock as their God hath.</p>
            <p>By this we ſee how the very Heathen believe they ought to be Imitaters of their God, although it were the Devil; and therefore when <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old did not walk after the Name, Manner, or Law of the Living God, the Prophet reproved <note place="margin">Mica 4. 5.</note> them in theſe words: <hi>All people will walk in the name of their God, and we will walk in the name of the Lord our God for ever and ever.</hi> And is not this a ſhame to Chriſtians, that ever the Words of a Heathen Idolatrous <hi>Virginian,</hi> ſhould dart the minds of ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men, that about the beginning of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, a long lock on the left ſide Mens heads, began to be a great faſhion; and not among or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Men, but the cheif in the Nation in that day, as the effigies of ſome do yet ſhew; ſo that hence it was that the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas <hi>Pilgr. l. 3. c. 6. ſect. 3.</hi>
               </note> ſorementioned Hiſtorian ſaith in expreſs terms, That our ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and unlovely love-locks had their original, birth, and pedigree, from the Heatheniſh Idolatrous <hi>Virginians,</hi> who took their pattern from their Devil-God <hi>Ocheus,</hi> who uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeared to them in the ſhape of a Man with a long black lock on the left ſide his head, hanging down to the ground.</p>
            <p>Now what ſaith the Scripture to the People of God? <hi>Be ye followers of God as dear Children; be ye followers together of me,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 1. Phil. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>and mark them which walk ſo, as ye have us for an example.</hi> Now then if we will be followers of God as his Children, we muſt hearken to our heavenly Father Counſel, who hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his mind (to inform the Churches) to his Apoſtles; and they teach us it is the mind of God, that Men ſhall not wear long hair; and therefore reproved ſuch as did wear long <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 14.</note> hair. So then for Men to wear long hair, or the long hair of Women, is againſt the Will and Mind of God, as hath been afore proved: Therefore if Men wear long hair, they be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the evil One, who taught the <hi>Virgi</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to wear long hair; firſt a long lock on the left ſide their head, as a ſign of ſubjection to him; and alſo taught the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and Babylonians of old, and alſo the ſpiritual <hi>Babylonians</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ians;</hi> and no doubt but the <hi>Sodomites</hi> too, for when the Ange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> came to <hi>Let</hi> in the form of Men, doubtleſs in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 4. Heb. 13. 2.</note> God created Man in reſpect of his hair, which all holy Men in all Age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> followed; to they ſuppoſed them to be <hi>Lots</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43039:22"/> and therefore as they hated <hi>Lot,</hi> whoſe righteous Soul they vexed with their evil Converſation, they hated all that went as he did; like the Men of late years, ſince long hair has been ſo much worn in this Nation, about fifty years ago, the Chriſtians that walked by the Rule of Gods Word, and wore their hair agreeable thereto, were by the rude Rabble mocked and called Roundheads, and hunted after by purſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; ſo that on a Lords Day, where they ſaw Men with ſhort hair go into a Houſe, then they like the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> old and young from every quarter compaſſed the Houſe to take them and abuſe them; ſome they impriſoned, ſome were baniſhed, and ſome afore in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days they hanged, namely <hi>Mr. Henry Borrow,</hi> Mr. <hi>Greenwood,</hi> Mr. <hi>Penry;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Borrow <hi>&amp; Mr</hi> Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, <hi>and Mr</hi> Penrys <hi>Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and more work for the Dean, where theſe mens ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings are ſhewed at large. Luke 8. Mat. 4. 17. Iſas. 49. 15. Rom. 6. 16. John</hi> 8. 44.</note> ſo that he that departed from this evil, long hair, of later years, for this cauſe made themſelves a Prey: But as the Seed of Gods Word is ſown on many places, ſome received it, as by the way ſide; theſe underſtood it not, for the Fowls or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ones ſteal it from them: Others receive it on ſtoney hearts, theſe wanting love to the truth, theſe in time of perſecution fall away: Others receive the Word as among thorns, to wit, the care pleaſures, and love of the World choaked it ſo, it withered away: All theſe began to be offended at the Word that commanded them to wear ſhort hair, ſeeing he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the evil wearing of long hair, made himſelf a prey; ſo that many of the Profeſſors began by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to let their hair grow till at laſt they could wear long hair as well as any: Now what ſaith the Scripture to them? <hi>His ſervants ye are whom ye obey:</hi> And did not Chriſt tell the <hi>Jews, Ye are of your father the Devil, whoſe work ye do?</hi> And hath it not been proved it is the Work of the evil One, to draw. Men from Gods Worth to obey his Word, from being adlmitator of God to he an limitater of him; ſo that the long hair in Men, which was learned, from him began to be ſo burdenſome, ſo chargeable to keep it clean and many the colour pleaſed them not, and ſome Mens hair curled not to their minds; ſo that the bread of deceit which ſeemed for a <note place="margin">Prov. 20.</note> while ſweet, but afterwards their mouths were filled with gravel: ſo that there was no content with Mens own long hair. And in this diſtreſs and vexation of mind, is sat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> opportunity to ſtir up Inſtruments to provoke to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:43039:22"/> degree of ſinning in this thing; ſo that whether, as <hi>Eve,</hi> the Women did perſwade their Hvsbands, that the onely way was for them to ſhave off all their hair, and might ſay, <note place="margin">Ezek. 44. 20.</note> 
               <hi>What although you are forbidden of God you ſhall not ſhave your heads, yet the Doctors ſay it is good for your health:</hi> And thus as <hi>Adam</hi> was perſwaded to take the forbidden thing, ſo were Men perſwaded to meddle with the forbidden thing, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding as plain a precept is given that Men ſhall not ſuffer their locks to grovv long, and that Men ſhall not put on Womans natural covering, as hath been afore proved, as vvas to <hi>Adam</hi> that he ſhould not eat of the forbidden fruit; yet as the one vvas ſin being forbidden, ſo vvas the other; as the one vvas forbidden Man, ſo is the other; as the one vvas taken in the breach of Gods Lavv, ſo is the othen; and as the breach of the Lavv vvas ſin in them, ſo it is novv; and and as the vvages of ſin vvas death to them, ſo it is novv in Men that vvear Womans long hair, Womans natural cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; and likevviſe ſin in Women that cut off their hair, their effeminate glory, and badge and ſign of their ſubjection to Men their Husbands for Men to vvear; and the more to be lamented, vven the Leaders of the People, that ſhould be Guides to poor Souls in the vvay of Righteouſneſs, are the Leaders of others, in this act of Unrighteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>What good vvill the vain boaſting of theſe Preachers do them in the laſt day? Let them hear vvhat the Great Judge vvill ſay to them, as it is vvritten, <hi>When ye ſhall ſay, Lord,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, have we not propheſied in thy name, and in thy name caſt out devils, and in thy name have done many wonderful works: I profeſs I never knew you, depart from me ye workers of iniquity,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 10. 27.</note> 
               <hi>for you are not my ſheep, becauſe my ſheep hear my voice and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me; neither have ye my ſeal, for every one that nameth the name of Jeſus, having this ſeal: let the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> depart from iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What then, are all gone out of the way in this particular, that are called Chriſtians? for whatſoever difference are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Men in other matters, they almoſt all agree to ſuffer their own locks to grow long, or elſe to wear the long hair of Women. Now to be plain with all ſorts of People, that hear the name Chriſtians without reſpect of Perſons or manner of their Religion, ſeeing the matter here treated of is,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43039:23"/> concerning the breach of GOD's Order in Nature one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Roman</hi> Relegion who make cutting Mens hair ſhort, to be a part of their Religious Order; ſo that as Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Prinn <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nloveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Love-locks p. 11. and his</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Gua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Pol. <hi>Tom. 1. p.</hi> 74.</note> ſay, Pope <hi>Benedict</hi> the Ninth injoyned all the <hi>Polonians,</hi> upon releaſe of <hi>Cazimiz</hi> the Firſt their King, who had entred into Religion, to cut their hair ſhort above their ears, and not to ſuffer it to grow long; yet theſe People how generally do they wear the long locks of Women in Perriwigs, and ſo tranſgreſs the Law of God in Nature, and other written Laws of God, and alſo the Decree of the Pope; and yet they plead for Infallibility, and that their Church cannot Err; whenas in this particular they are but Hearers of the Word, and not Doers of the ſame; all ſuch, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>James,</hi> their Religion is in vain. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, There are another People that preſs all People that hear them, to mind the Teachings of the Light within, becauſe they ſay this Light is Chriſt, and this Light every Man hath: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 16.</note> It is granted, that as Chriſt is the Eternal Word of God, by whom all things was created, is the Light that every Man and Woman hath, that is born into the World, and this Light is but natural, as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The firſt man is of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John. 1. 9. 1 Cor. 15. 46, 47. Eph. 5. 14. 2 Tim. 3. 2. Jude v. 19.</note> 
               <hi>the earth earthy;</hi> ſo that that was not firſt that is ſpiritual, but that which is natural, and after which is ſpiritual; which ſpiritual Light all Men have not, for all Men have not Faith, neither have all Men the Spirit of Chriſt, as it is written, <hi>They ſeparate themſelves, ſenſual, having not the Spirit:</hi> Yet theſe Men who Boaſt they have the Spirit of Chriſt, why then are they not led by it? for as many as are led by the Spirit of Chriſt, they are the Children of God; which Spirit teacheth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 14.</note> Man he ſhall not ſuffer his locks to grow long; and alſo the Light or Law in Nature telleth them the ſame; for doth not <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 14.</note> even Nature it ſelf teach you, that if a man have long hair, it is a ſhame to him? and yet theſe Men either ſuffer their locks to grow long, or elſe (the very Teachers among them) wear the long hair of Women in Perriwigs, as well as others among them; let theſe Men for ſhame no more boaſt of the Light within, ſeeing they know not the Teachings of the Light of Nature, unto whom it may be juſtly ſaid (as Chriſt ſaid to the Jews that rejected Chriſt the Light of Life without, and he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43039:23"/> written Word of God that taught them that he was Chriſt, the Light of Life, <hi>John</hi> 8. 24. which if they believed not, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 8. 24.</note> they ſhould die in their ſins) the Light in them was Darkneſs; how great then is that darkneſs in theſe Men that boaſt of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 23.</note> Light within, and have not the Light in Nature, to teach them it is a ſhame for a Man to wear long hair; much more a ſhame for them to wear the long hair of Women in Perriwigs; no nor yet the Women-Teachers among them have not ſo much Light to teach that Men ſhould not unman themſelves to become effeminate, in coveting their Glory, in wearing on their heads the long hair of Women, Womans natural co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering; ſo that theſe have not yet the Light of Nature tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in this thing, but have alſo rejected the Word of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 8. 9.</note> Lord; What Wiſdom is in them, as ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To all other Chriſtians who in Word do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the written Word of God to be the Rule to walk by, both in the matter of Faith and Worſhip, and alſo in things natural; yet in this particular they are but Hearers of the Word, and not Doers of the ſame, and ſo deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in that they plead that upon ſome caſes a Man may wear the long hair of Women in Perriwigs: Their plea is to this effect: You know in the late Perſecution how the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, and many other principal Men in the Congregations, have been ſought for by the Informers, to be taken and carried to Priſon, ſo that they did wear Perrwigs to diſguiſe themſelves; if it had not been for that, they would not have wore them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We are taught by the Doctrine of the Goſpel, that we may not do evil that good may come; for a good Tree <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 8.</note> bringeth nor forth corrupt Fruit, ſaith Chriſt; and ſeeing it hath pleaſed God to give us an unexpected deliverance, ſo <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. 43.</note> that we may ſay as <hi>Judah</hi> did of old, when the Lord turned again the Captivity of <hi>Sion,</hi> we were like them that dream: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 126. 1, 2, 3. Iſai. 49. 23. Rev.</hi> 12. 16, 16.</note> The Lord hath done great things for ur, in giving us a King according to his pomife to be a Nurſing Father; ſo that the Earth hath helped the Woman and opened her mouth in the Kings Declaration, and ſwallowed up the Flouds of Penal Statutes, and whatſoever elſe the Dragon caſt out of his mouth by his Inſtruments, to carry away the Woman, the Church of Chriſt, either to priſon, or to baniſhment, or to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43039:24"/> death, ſo cruel and inhumane are the Laws of this Nation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 107. 29. Rev. 8. 1. Acts</hi> 9. 31.</note> her, as in an Abſtract of the Penel Laws lately publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed doth ſhew; but bleſſed be God who hath given ſo great a Calm, after ſo great a Storm, to enjoy, as the Lord Jeſus hath proclaimed in his Goſpel, That <hi>the Tares</hi> (the Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers) <hi>and the Wheat</hi> (the godly) <hi>ſhall live together in the field,</hi> (which himſelf hath expounded to be the World) freely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 30.</note> moleſtation to enjoy all their Rights and Priviledges, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the different Perſwaſions in matters of their Faith and Religion, as the <hi>Perizzites, Hittites,</hi> and others did <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg. 3. 3, 4. Mat.</hi> 8. 28.</note> in <hi>Canaan,</hi> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> had the Land in their poſſeſſion; <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every one ſhall give an account for himſelf at the great day of Iudgment;</hi> and therefore this general Rule is given to all Chriſtians, <hi>Love the Brotherhood, fear God, honour the King,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor. 5. 10. Eccl. 11. 14. 1 Pet. 2. 17. 1 Tim.</hi> 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>with ſupplications, prayers, and interceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for all men, for Kings and for all that are in authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſs and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, for this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour.</hi> So that ſeeing the cauſe of the Plea for wearing of Perriwigs is removed, what is the reaſon both the miniſters and others do wear Perriwigs, and alſo many of them that wore no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwigs in the heat of Perſecution, do wear the long hair of Women ſince.</p>
            <p>For this another pretended Plea is made, You know that many of the Miniſters are Aged, and others are tender and weak; ſo that they having wore Perriwigs ſo long, if they ſhould leave them off, and wear their hair according to the Word of God, polled or ſhorn, it might endanger their health, if not their lives and all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The moſt Wiſe God when he made Man, gave him the whole Plenty of the Earth for his Food and comfort; and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 17. 17.</note> God was pleaſed but to reſerve one Tree, commanding him he ſhould not eat of the Fruit thereof: yet Man was not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but he muſt deſire to eat of the Fruit forbidden him, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he ſuffered by ſo doing. Even ſo the moſt Wiſe God hath given Man the whole plenty of the Earth, fit for Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or Covering, to keep him warm; and hath forbidden him but one thing, he ſhall not wear to keep him warm, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Womans long hair, or his own locks long; yet Man is ſo unſatisfied a Creature, that the one thing forbidden him, he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43039:24"/> veteth to wear, and will wear it, notwithſtanding God hath <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut. 22. 5. 1 Cor. 11. 7. Pſal. 19. 13. Rom. 14. 22. Jer.</hi> 13. 23.</note> commanded he ſhall not; ſo that the Teachers in ſpecial can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be igorant of it; let them beware they be not charged with the ſin of Preſumption, condemning themſelves in the thing they allow, and ſo the ſaying of the Lord be not juſtly charged on them, <hi>Can the Ethiopian change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots? then may ye alſo do good, that are accuſtomed to do evil.</hi> So then there is no plea againſt Gods plain Law, to excuſe the Breakers thereof; for if it might, then <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi> might have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped God would have ſpared his life, when out of a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent he put forth his hand to ſtay the Ark from falling: or <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 23. 10.</note> King <hi>Saul</hi> might have hoped the Lord would not have reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him from being King, when he in the breach of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſpared the fat Cattel of <hi>Amaleck,</hi> to offer in Sacrifices to the Lord; but he was told, <hi>Hath the Lord ſo great delight</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam. 15. 19, 20, 21, 22, 23. Rev. 5. 10. 1 Pet. 2. 9. Deut. 6. 4, 5, 6, 7. Deut. 29. 29. Acts 2. 39. Pſal. 128. 3. Exod. 12. 26. Deut. 6. 20. Eph. 6. 4. Deut. 31. 12, 13, Iſai. 44. 5. Exod.</hi> 15. 2.</note> 
               <hi>in Burnt-Offerings, as in obeying the voice of the Lord:</hi> Even ſo let all Chriſtians beware the Lord doth not reject them from being Kings and Prieſts unto God, out of the Kingdom of Chriſt, in diſobeying the Command of the Lord; and alſo in training up their Children in that evil practice; whenas they are commanded to train them up in the Commands of God, ſeeing Revealed things belong to us and to our Children, ſo the promiſe of life in Chriſt is to us and to our Children; for as they are Olive-plants, born in the Lords Covenant, which is the Kingdom of God, ſo are they of the Kingdom of Grace; and therefore are we commanded to take them with us to the place of Gods Worſhip, ſo when they ask what meaneth by this Service or Ordinance, we may teach them, bringing them up in the Admonition of the Lord, teaching them what God hath done for them, and what he requireth (as they grow in years) of them; that ſo in time they may come forth in the face of the Congregation, and confeſs, <hi>I am the Lords, and he is become my Salvation; he is my Fathers God, and I will exalt him:</hi> But how is this Work advanced in Children, when they are taught to walk in the ſhame to Nature? the Female Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren going with their hair ſhorn like Boys, and the Male Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with Girls hair on their heads. O what a kind of Chriſtians are theſe, that have changed both in themſelves and their Children, the natural uſe, into that which is againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture!</p>
            <p>Yet a word to the Female Sex only, who come into the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43039:25"/> with their hair the moſt part uncovered, ſhort o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhorn, to the ſhame of their Natures, as afore-ſhew'd: as they may read, that that Woman that had her hair uncovered before the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb,</hi> 5. 18.</note> Lord, in the Aſſembly or Worſhip of God, were only ſuch Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that their Husbands accuſed them for being diſhoneſt, ſo were tried by the Law for Jealouſie. Mr. <hi>Ainſ.</hi> in his Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the words, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncover the Womans head,</hi> noteth what the manner was, as the <hi>Hebrews</hi> write, that the Prieſt uncover'd the Womans hair, and untied the locks of her head to make her unſeemly; hence ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Is it comely for a woman to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor. 11. 13. Prov.</hi> 7. 10</note> 
               <hi>pray unto unto God with her head,</hi> to wit, her hair, <hi>uncovered?</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid he ſaw a Woman with the Attire of an Harlot; what can this be but the Womans laying out her hair for ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; which the Apoſtle ſaith is an act of ſhameleſneſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſty. Now the place where this Attire of an Harlot is ſet forth, is on the forehead; and this is proved by a borrowed ſpeech the Prophet taketh from the practice of common Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, when he charged <hi>Judah</hi> with her imperious ſpiritual Whoredoms, as it is written, <hi>She had a Whores forhead, as one not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. 3.</note> 
               <hi>aſhamed:</hi> Now ſhall Chriſtian Women do that act or thing that ſhall repreſent them immodeſt in the face of the Church? no, ſince the Spouſe of Chriſt when ſuffered many ſlanderous abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes at the hands of falſe Teachers in point of modeſty, ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by her complaint, all the abuſes under the name of taking her vail from her; ſo that the name Vail, ſaith Mr. <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> on <hi>Song</hi> 5. 7. hath its name in the original of ſpreading, as being ſpread over her head to cover her: ſuch Vails were worn by Women, partly for ornament, as appeareth by <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3. 23. partly for modeſty, and in ſign of ſubjection to Men, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially their Husbands, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 6, 7, 10. and a Husband is to the Wife a covering of the eyes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. 16. ſo the taking away of her Vail, ſeemeth to be a note of infamy, diſloyalty, or diſhone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, imputed unto her, as of Idolatry, Hereſie, Schiſm, and the like; ſo ſhe was ſpoiled of her good Name and Reputation, and accounted among the light and lewd Women; for it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23. 25, 26. that they uſed to treat diſhoneſt Women ſo. By all which it appeareth, it is a ſhame for any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Woman to wear her hair uncovered; nay it is commonly ſeen, that if a ſtrange Man come at unawares where a modeſt Woman is but a combing her hair, away ſhe ſteps aſide to hide her ſelf, or elſe caſteth ſomething over her head to cover her
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43039:25"/> hair. Now ſhall Women not be aſhamed to lay out their hair for adorning, and turning it up on their foreheads like a Squir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils tail, and cut their hair ſhort, as ſhorn by their ears, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that well-ſet hair, as the wanton Daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> did <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iai.</hi> 23. 24.</note> of old? for which the Lord threatned them; that inſtead of well-ſet hair, he would ſend them baldneſs; as came on them <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam. 1. 8. &amp;</hi> 2. 10. 20.</note> with a vengeance; a warning to the Daughters of <hi>Sion.</hi> Now therefore they ſhould take example by the holy Women of old, who gave their brazen Looking glaſſes they uſed to dreſs their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod. 38. 8. Rev. 1. 6. Tit.</hi> 3. 5.</note> Bodies in, to make a Laver, wherein by Faith they ſaw their ſins waſhed away in the Blood of Chriſt, who hath ſaved us by the waſhing of Regeneration, and renewing of the Holy Ghoſt; ſo that with <hi>Mary</hi> they ſhould delight themſelves in chuſing the better part. And,</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Will not Men and Women believe, that the moſt Wiſe God hath made all his Works ſo perfect in Wiſdom, that they ought to be fully ſatisfied to let every thing remain in that holy order, the great Creator hath to admiration ſet them in, in reſpect of every part, uſe, and nature, God hath ſet every thing belonging to Man and Womans Body; ſo that hereupon the Prophet ſaith, <hi>How fearfully and wonderfully am I made!</hi> So <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 14.</note> that as long hair is given Woman for a ſign in her according to her Sex, to teach her ſubjection to Man, how dare. Man look to God-ward, when he hath changed Gods Order in Nature, to take Womans long hair and wear on his head? and not only ſo, but not withſtanding what God hath ſaid, that Man cannot make one hair white or black, teaching Man thereby not to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 36.</note> preſume to change his hair; if God hath given him gray hairs, not to ſhave it off, and to cover his head with a contrary colour hair; ſeeing the Spirit of God ſaith, <hi>The beauty of old men is the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 02. 29.</note> 
               <hi>gray head, and the hoary head is a crown of glory, if it be found in the way of righteouſneſs.</hi> Now do not Men deſpiſe Gods Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip in nature? and is it not a ſin in them to ſhave their gray <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 31.</note> hairs, and wear on their head ſome womaniſh youthful colour'd hair. Again, the Lord hath taught his People his providenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al care he hath towards his People, from the very natural hairs of their head, as it is written, <hi>Even the very hairs of your</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 7.</note> 
               <hi>head are numbred:</hi> Doth the Lord Jeſus ſpeak of Womens long hair in Perriwigs on Mens heads? no ſure, Men were never ſo void of the Teaching of Nature in any Age of the World as this; the very Locuſts were not ſo charged, as Men may be <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. 7, 8.</note>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:43039:26"/> now; their hair was but as the hair of Women, but now the the Miniſters of the Goſpel have faces of Men, but the very hair of Women; how can theſe Men in Prayer to God draw any Petitions to God, as touching Gods providential care from theſe words, <hi>All the hairs of our head are numbred;</hi> when <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 30.</note> at that time they have ſhaved off all their own natural hair, and have on their heads the ſtinking excrements of Women, without mocking of God: It muſt needs be a horrid ſin in Man, that doth that which hindreth the dictates of the Spirit, that it cannot have free egreſs, to draw Arguments through the whole Scripture, with <hi>David,</hi> as it is written, <hi>When I am old</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71. 18.</note> 
               <hi>and gray-headed, forget me not:</hi> For we know in Prayer when we go near to God in that Work, we know not what to pray for, as we ought, but as the Spirit helpeth our infirmities. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26.</note> What deeper ſence of the promiſe of God is there from any Scripture to be gathered of God, keeping his People <hi>as the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his eye,</hi> than that <hi>the hairs of our head are all numbred.</hi> So that <hi>David</hi> in his great Afflictions, as he was a figure of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 12.</note> Chriſt, in his Prayer to God ſaith, <hi>They are more than the hairs of mine head.</hi> This may teach us how we may not wear any hair but our own natural hair, as Gods Servants by the Spirit <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen. 42. 38. Deut. 32. Job 15. 10. 1 Sam. 12. 2. 1 King. 1. 52. 2 Sam.</hi> 14. 11.</note> had occaſion to ſpeak of them, with reſpect to the number, as alſo the colour: So when King <hi>Solomon</hi> would promiſe a firm protection to any one, according to the Power of a King, <hi>There ſhall not an hair of him fall to the ground:</hi> ſo <hi>David, As the Lord liveth, there ſhall not one hair of thy Son fall to the Earth.</hi> How can Men plead with God to remember his Promiſe from that Scripture, That <hi>the Hairs of our head are all numbred,</hi> when Man hath on his head a falſe hair?</p>
            <p>Again, Hath not God given to Men diverſities of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances with admiration, with comely proportion, ſo that one Man is the more eaſily known from another? Now if a Man ſhould put on his face, to wit, a Miniſter, a Vizard, a falſe face, as he hath on his head falſe hair; when he teacheth the People, what Man or Woman would endure to hear him? and is it not as lawful for a Man to wear a falſe countenance, as a falſe hair, both being abominable? Now ye that fear God, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider theſe things, and remember what Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>That which is highly eſteemed among men, is abominable in the ſight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43039:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
